<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumphs of King Iames the First, of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, King; defender of the faith Published vpon his Maiesties aduertisement to all the kings, princes, and potentates of Christendome, and confirmed by the wonderfull workes of God, declared in his life. Deuoted, dedicated, and consecrated to the most excellent prince Henry Prince of Wales.</title>
            <author>Marcelline, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1634:9, 721:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumphs of King Iames the First, of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, King; defender of the faith Published vpon his Maiesties aduertisement to all the kings, princes, and potentates of Christendome, and confirmed by the wonderfull workes of God, declared in his life. Deuoted, dedicated, and consecrated to the most excellent prince Henry Prince of Wales.</title>
                  <author>Marcelline, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Brittaines Bursse, [by William Jaggard] for Iohn Budge, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By George Marcelline.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: King Iames triumphant.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (reel 721:5) and the Bodleian Library (reel 1634:9).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Triumphs of King Iames THE FIRST, Of Great BRITTAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, King; <hi>DEFENDER OF THE FAITH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed vpon his Maieſties aduertiſement to all the Kings, Princes, and Potentates of Chriſtendome, and confirmed by the wonderfull Workes of GOD, declared in his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deuoted, Dedicated, and Conſecrated to the moſt excellent</hi> Prince Henry <hi>Prince</hi> of Wales.</p>
            <p>Printed at Brittaines Burſſe, for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are there to be ſolde, 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the High, Mighty, and</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> Eldeſt Sonne to the King, <hi>Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>Duke of</hi> Cornwall, <hi>and</hi> Rothſay: Earle of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and Knight of the <hi>moſt Noble Order of the</hi> Garter, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>¶ Moſt generous and redoubted Prince, The Honour and Ornament of your age; The Hope of your people; The Subiect and Obiect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their moſt happy wiſhes dependeth; The STARRE of their faireſt Fortune; The COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MET of dreadfull terrour to their enemies; The <hi>Index, Abſtract,</hi> or <hi>Compendium</hi> of the very grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Princes whatſoeuer.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere, vpon the rich Piller of your glorious name, do I hang vp <hi>The Trophees</hi> &amp; the <hi>Honour</hi> of MY KING your <hi>Father,</hi> ſowne through <hi>France,</hi> and diſperſed ouer the whole world. Such holie ſpoiles are worthie your auouching, becauſe they are due vnto none other, but onelie vnto your HIGHNESSE, in regarde
<pb facs="tcp:12130:4"/>that a perſon who is ſo neere vnto you, hath conquered &amp; won them: And his <hi>Triumphant Triumphes,</hi> are the auguries, harbingers, &amp; vant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currers of your infallible fortunes to come, euen as your owne Vertues do ſerue for a pattern and example, to them of MY LORD the Duke your Brother.</p>
            <p>Accept them then <hi>My Lord,</hi> &amp; by your fauorable looks, giue them all a ſpeaking-power, as the Sunnes reflectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did on the Image of <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> And beleeue, that as one of yours, you ſhall finde me readier to lay hand on my ſword for you, then on my pen, and would rather ſpend my blood then mine Inke, for your honour and ſeruice, in al, and by all,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My young</hi> CAESAR, <hi>and great</hi> ALEXANDER.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Eye of</hi> Europe, <hi>the Soule, the Heart, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of all thy neighbours;</hi> France, <hi>Mother of curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and our ancient friend:</hi> Suffer, that (with a voice of Braſſe) I may make heard through all the Corners of the earth, &amp; euen to thoſe worldes which yet are furtheſt off, cry out to that <hi>Iacobine</hi> Monke, and that <hi>Proſelite</hi> PELLITIER, <hi>Do no euil at al vnto my King.</hi> For ſo cryed out the Sonne of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> dumbe all his life time before, vntill hee ſaw the ſword drawne to wound his father. If the childe for the Father, why not then the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect for his Prince? Their loue ought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or equall, &amp; (in ſemblable actions) alike alſo ought to bee their duties, becauſe the people are helde to be the Princes Children.
<pb facs="tcp:12130:5"/>For I ſee, that theſe two audacious and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous <hi>Phaetons,</hi> do labour by their flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering anſweres (as with a <hi>Delphian</hi> ſword) to open the boſome or breaſt of MY KING, to ſtrike at his heart with a deadly ſtab, and to giue him the lie more couertly, then <hi>Tortus</hi> (to his ſhame) hath doone, coueting to impreſſe lies and falſities in the ſoules of euery one.</p>
            <p>Their painted ſpeeches and goodly prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, makes my haire ſtand vp as affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, pales my countenance, ſmites my hart, &amp; teares open my lippes, to entreat you (good <hi>Frenchmen</hi>) to credite them no further, then <hi>Our King</hi> hath done. Hee alwayes deriueth ſound iudgement from words, &amp; by the verie mouing of the toong he knoweth the harts of them that make ſuch Orations to him. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in beholding their books, he hath ſaide with God, <hi>Hilabijs me honorant, cor aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eorum longe eſt a me. Theſe men honor me with their lips, but their harts are far off from me.</hi> In like maner there is nothing more daungerous then the teeth of a Serpent hid vnder greene hearbes, and the throat of a wolfe, hauing on a ſheeps
<pb facs="tcp:12130:5"/>habit. Wo be to them that cal euill good, and good euill; that make darkneſſe light, and light darkneſſe, and that call bitterneſſe ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſweetneſſe bitternes. Wo be to you <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſies, Hypocrites,</hi> for you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe both ſea and land, to the end, to make one <hi>Proſelite:</hi> and when he is made, you yeild him vp as the Sonne of Hell, doouble worſe then your ſelues.</p>
            <p>What impudence was it in a cloiſtred Prieſt, &amp; in a priuat perſon, to ſhew himſelfe in open field, to cope with a great and powerful king, when Kinges haue beene at all times without Peere, and free from fight, except it were with others kings? Honor is not to be had, but by an equal: &amp; <hi>Alexander,</hi> being deſirous to win the prize, in the courſe of the <hi>Olimpian</hi> games, demanded continually: <hi>Is there any kings that runne?</hi> The like may our King very well que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: <hi>Is there any Kings that anſwere?</hi> Jt is to them to whom his Maieſty hath directed his aduertiſement, and it is to them only to make anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monarkes, Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> where are your Prouoſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals
<pb facs="tcp:12130:6"/>then? Where are your <hi>Lictours</hi> and <hi>Sergeants,</hi> to ſeize on theſe ſaucy gameſters? Where are your Lawes and Edicts, to puniſh theſe proud preſumers, that durſt ſet footing within your Liſts, to ſteppe before you in ſo faire a Race or Carriere? Stirre <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> lay hold on theſe baſe Hackny-runners, in ſo braue a fight, and do you beat downe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence of theſe raſh headed <hi>Athletes,</hi> or male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part Champions. There lackes Tortures for <hi>Tortus,</hi> to breake the bridles of ſuch ſilly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſoules, and bolſter their crazed braines a little better; to the end, to make <hi>Coeffeteau</hi> confeſſe, and <hi>Pelletier</hi> profeſſe the truth, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, according to the rule of truth it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe prooues, are to bee vanquiſhed with other Reaſons, then thoſe whereby they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to refute them, elſe it wil neuer be done. Hereſy findeth daily ſomething to re-ſay, and to confound Paper withall: ſome meanes to ſaue himſelfe either by flight, or obſtinacy of opinion, becauſe he wil neuer confeſſe his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, much leſſe deliuer vp his Armes. Euen ſo the <hi>Phariſies</hi> and the <hi>Saduces,</hi> being beaten
<pb facs="tcp:12130:6"/>downe by the mouth Diuine, would yet ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly exalt themſelues again, without confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing either their fal, or the offence. So <hi>Pericles,</hi> throwne headlong downe, and euen almoſt buried in the duſt, would yet perſwade the whole Theater, that he deſerued to be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So that <hi>Hippomachus</hi> (of whome <hi>Plinie</hi> ſpeaketh) and the other of the <hi>Acolians,</hi> would needs be proclaimed victorious conquerors, after they had breathed forth theirs ſoules vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their enemies feete. And ſo this <hi>Antaeus,</hi> and his companions, already ſtifled in the gripes of our <hi>Chriſtian Hercules,</hi> would faine perſwade the worlde, that being themſelues vanquiſhed, yet they ſtand vp ſtill as vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers. All ſuch brablings and contentious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, doe but whet on Choller, and harden bad ſpirits, as being more apt to moue ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſobedience, then to affoorde anie fruitfull edifying.</p>
            <p>Let then their ſhameleſſe fore-heads bee circkled with Crownes, ſuch as the Romains vſed in their <hi>Conſull</hi> feſtiuals, for their <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Monſters, rather then any anſweare bee
<pb facs="tcp:12130:7"/>made vnto them, except it be by the hand of <hi>Thomas Dury,</hi> our Maiſter <hi>Guillaume.</hi> Let the Laurell wreaths be wrung out of their hands, to impale the victorious head of our IAMES, truely <hi>Triumphant,</hi> ouer <hi>Pagan Idolatrie,</hi> and <hi>Popish Hereſie,</hi> which is the ſubiect of this my preſent labour, and the whole deſſeign of this diſcourſe, as appeareth in the Frontiſpice of the main building. Thus are <hi>His Trophees</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and limmed (through by an vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Penſill) in his victories, deriued from the writing of his Royall Aduertiſement.</p>
            <p>This is the full ayme of mine intention <hi>(Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious French-men)</hi> and that which I deſire to ſhew vnto you <hi>(Deare Children of Heauen)</hi> to the end, that you may not ſuffer your ſelues to bee perſwaded in the contrarie, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Language, ſubtle Arguings, Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries, and captious arguments of this Doctor Diuinity-deſtroyer, and the diſcourſing <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſte,</hi> leaſt of wiſe French-men, you becom with them, mad and inſenſed <hi>Galathians.</hi> The very written book it ſelfe doth furniſh vs with ſtrength ſufficient, to vanquiſh and conuince
<pb facs="tcp:12130:7"/>all the anſwerers of the worlde, and their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; not turning any one leafe of his book, but it deliuereth many moſt expreſſe Texts of the holy Scriptures, as many goodly places out of the holy fathers, as many Canons of the chiefeſt Counſellers, with many rich &amp; ſtrong arguments, and al ſet downe by his Maieſty.</p>
            <p>It is to you <hi>(Generous French-men)</hi> that I ſpeake this, and to whom I deſire to make it manifeſt: for though the ſpeaking, or willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to make it knowne to you of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſhould be but in me as loſt labor, yet muſt J needs ſpeake it againe, beeing no more but what you know, what you haue ſeene, and what hath bin publiſhed. So many mouthes are as ſo many Trumpets of his greatneſſe in great <hi>Brittaine;</hi> ſo many hearts, they are as ſo many Temples of his vertues; and ſo many ſoules, are as many Vowes and Sacrifices to his faire name. Among them, J am but as one voice, yet now driuen to the vniuerſall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of the whol worlds voices. For if my voice could bee vnderſtoode from the Eaſt to the Weſt, from the North to the South: nay, if it could pierce from this low center of the earth
<pb facs="tcp:12130:8"/>to the higheſt circumference of the Jmperiall heauen: I would cal al Noble Spirits to com, to ſee Idolatry ſubdued, and Hereſie vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and I would entreate them, to beeleue that which I ſay vnto you, for an aſſured ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whereof Heauen, Earth, Men, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, are faithfull and vnreprooueable witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. My words do ſauour rather of the ſalt of a pure affection, then the Oyle of ſupple flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; My penne ſhal neuer be <hi>Ioabs</hi> Dagger, to ſtab <hi>Abner</hi> backward: My life is innocent, my heart Chriſtian, My tongue to Scottiſh, &amp; he is too good and wiſe a King, to bee flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any.</p>
            <p>But to accommodate my ſelfe to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of theſe inſolents, who haue made <hi>French</hi> anſweres to a <hi>Latine.</hi> Booke, I ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to expreſſe my conceite of their Idiome, and imitate (as wel as I can) the ſteppes of our <hi>French Orators.</hi> Wherein I will looſe no time for excuſing my ſelfe, either for my harſh and vnelegant language, fearing the reply (in el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der time) made by <hi>Cato</hi> vnto the Hiſtorian <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:8"/>
            <p>The courteous and Charitable <hi>Frenchman,</hi> in conſidering the good and free will, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I march on in this matter, and for his inſtruction; will amiably correct the Errours of my Penne and the Preſſe, which manie (in like fauour) haue amended in our Language. In this affaire, their blowes do touch vs, their Ieſts and Sportes do inuite vs, their Reaſons do driue vs, and their daily deſires ought to mooue vs.</p>
            <p>But if any baſe and creeping ſoule, if anie deiected ſpirite, or if ſome Monke or Prieſt ſhall recreate his leyſure by this writing, and purge his ſalt ſoule of thoſe foule ſlaunders, breathed foorth with ſo many wry mouthes, &amp; apiſh faces, with ſuch bending the browes, and ſnuffes in the noſe, and which (no doubt) he will vſe in reading this worke: One Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell braunch of MY KING (onely) ſhall bee my Warrant, from the ſparkeling flaſhes of ſuch falſe fires, and his glorious Name ſhall ſerue me as the Shield of <hi>Minerua,</hi> againſt all their impoyſoned Arrowes of <hi>Neſſus</hi> and <hi>Philocteres.</hi> Let euery <hi>Momus, Zoylus,</hi> and all
<pb facs="tcp:12130:9"/>inſenced Cenſurers examine this little Booke Letter by letter; let them meaſure the Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, weigh the Words, controule the points and Virgulers; let them peruſe the Periods, count the Pages, and turne ouer the leaues: I will proteſt onely for my Apology, that I haue taken the Rule, Squire, Plummet, and compaſſe in forming it, only to enform them in a ſolid truth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, cruell apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, briſtle not vppe your haires againſt mee; affrighted horrours, ſeeke not to ſhake my ſoule anie more; panicke terrours, leaue my heart at large, and my tongue at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie; to the end, that I may bidde them; <hi>Go out, go out of Babylon flye from behind her, Be not ouerthrowne in her iniquities. But publiſh this with a loude voyce, as a Song of Tryumph, and ſpeake it vnto the vtmost part of
<pb facs="tcp:12130:9"/>the Earth:</hi> THE ETERNALL HATH RRDEEMED HIS SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VANT IAMES.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Farewell then France.</hi> My well beloued, and take this for thy preſent, and the guift of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</salute>
               <dateline>¶ <hi>From</hi> Alethia, <date>
                     <hi>towards the VVinter</hi> Solſtice, <hi>or the decreaſing of the</hi> Romiſh Religion, <hi>and aſcending of the truely</hi> Catholique <hi>and Reformed.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:12130:10"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12130:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>King IAMES Triumphant.</hi> OR, The Trophees of the <hi>KING</hi> of great <hi>BRITTAINE, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>P, on your Palm-trees (ô ye mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals) run all to Lawrels or flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Bayes: on to the wild <hi>Oliue,</hi> let vs fill our handes with flouring braunches of the Pine; all which, neuer wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to plaite Wreathes, Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>plets, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronets of honor for this worthy <hi>Pancratiaſte.</hi> Gather greene Maple, to beſet round about the body of this <hi>Triumphant VVraſtler.</hi> Cal for Trumpets and Clarions, to celebrate the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory &amp; bleſsing of our KING IAMES.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12130:11"/>Let vs found forth the praiſes of that inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Monarch, who inuiteth all Kings vnto his Royall Triumph. Let vs paſſe thorough a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrall fire of venomous tongues (bee it eyther the poiſon of Hereſie, or of enuy, or of ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous detraction) or of immolated Beaſts. Let vs prepare the hauty Trophees of his heroick actions, farre more ſurpaſsing in noiſe, ſound, and glorie, then all the pompous Triumphes of <hi>Pompey, Aemilius, Scipio,</hi> or <hi>Veſpaſian.</hi> Let vs inſculpe and carue them, not in the Marble of <hi>Quarrera,</hi> the Alablaſter of <hi>Venice,</hi> the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiry</hi> of <hi>Guinea,</hi> nor yet in Iuory; not in Braſſe or Copper, nor yet in Siluer, or in the richeſt enammeled Golde: but in the Temple of <hi>Memory,</hi> and in the hearts of all men. To the end, that altogether in one vnanimity may ſing with mee, not in an halfe or lowe, but in a full and lowde voyce, cheerfully ſounding out theſe two Wordes, theſe ioyfull Words, this IO PAEON.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let all mortals now reioyce,</l>
                  <l>And applaud with hands and voyce:</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12130:11"/>
                  <l>When they heare the noiſe and ſound,</l>
                  <l>(Which like thunder doth rebound)</l>
                  <l>Of King JAMES the honour great,</l>
                  <l>To whom God from his mercies ſeat,</l>
                  <l>(Beyond all other elſe) hath ſhowne,</l>
                  <l>Such loue, as like was neuer knowne.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Chaſt Spouſe of Ieſus Chriſt, thou being the glorie of his Victories, thou being the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his Triumphes, and thou being the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of his iuſt fights: Come, ô come, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from <hi>Libanon,</hi> looke downe from the Mountaine top of <hi>Amana,</hi> from the height of <hi>Shamit</hi> and <hi>Hermon:</hi> Come ſweete Empreſſe of the world, and work ſo graciouſly, that the homagers of thy Faith may (at the leaſt) bring victorious Palmes, and lay them before his feete, whom God hath heer eſtabliſhed vpon earth, and hath made choiſe of at this inſtant, for thy deliuerance out of the handes of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Antichriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſee how Heauen hath confirm'd his throne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Induitur chlamidem, regnique inſigne vetuſti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12130:12"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Geſtat laeua decus, cinguntur tempora vitta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Albente, ac lateride more accingitur enſis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>In this maner is it, that the true Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth the triumphal Arche of MY KING, euen of all the Sacred Orders which hee hath in his Royall Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and on that very day, when he deliuered vs from the dreadful fire, the Flames whereof would haue reached vp to the Starres, and the Aſhes vnto the center of the earth, in the yeare of Grace, MDCV. and in this yeare alſo, the day of his birth in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Which Nation alſo, being deſirous to eleuate their piety vnto the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of his glory, hath imitated the Emperour <hi>Macrinus,</hi> who to deify <hi>Antoninꝰ,</hi> erected him a Statue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſitting in his Throne, adorned in all his Royall Ornaments.</p>
            <p>This is the magnificent furniſhment, which the reformed religion hath prouided for him, as being due to the Preſeruer of her Sacred priuiledges, and to the <hi>Guardian</hi> of her intire purity. To the end, that he ſhold be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged through the whole world, for <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12130:12"/>of the Faith,</hi> and appeare dreadfull to his enemies, as the ouer-commer of <hi>Monſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs go on then to his fights, march on to his allarums, &amp; ſearch into his victory, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto his Triumphes; where we ſhal firſt of all beholde, that it is not a ſingle fight, or Combate of man to man, but the encounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of one man (halfe an Angell) with the darke and infernall powers of Hell.</p>
            <p>For the Enemy, both of God and of Kings preſumeth into his preſence, to ſearch into, &amp; to diſpute the ſence of the Goſpell, in the brightnes of Flames, and in horrible exploites of ſeuerity and cruelty. His Squadrons are prepared, and conſiſte of Furyes, <hi>Scolopen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Stellions, Phalanges,</hi> and <hi>Philemons,</hi> more mad and enraged then thoſe of <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> more furious then thoſe of <hi>Hercules,</hi> &amp; much more frantick then that <hi>Aiax,</hi> whom <hi>Sophocles</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth in his Tragedy. The Keyes ſerued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Courtle-Axes,</hi> not to open &amp; ſhut the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, but to gripe and graſpe vp all the Gold and Siluer, yea, all the wealthy abundance of <hi>Great Brittaine.</hi> The Sheepe-hooke, Croſier,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12130:13"/>or Paſtorall Staffe, ſerued to catch vp the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sheepe in all the Lords flocke. And the Watch-word was nothing elſe, but <hi>Kil, Burn,</hi> and <hi>Maſſacre.</hi> As for the followers, they were fully armed from head to the foote, with fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, rage, and malice, hauing their harts filled with Sulpher and Brimſtone, to burn, ſpoile, and deſolate all. Their pieces of Ordinance carried ſix and thirty barrels of Gun-powder, beſide Billets and Faggots, and great ſharpe-pointed bars of Iron. And the ſound of their Trumpets, was, <hi>Pereant amici, modo inimici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O good God, what kind of armes are theſe? The Church, the onely daughter of Heauen, the Virgin feated on the hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> was ſhee euer a Murdreſſe? Was ſhe euer taxed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cruelty? Or did ſhe euer drowne the world in bloud? Alas, hath not (much rather) perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution bin her legitimate legacy in the world? Hath not infinit ſtore of afflictions bin hir pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony and inheritance? And the crown of martirdom, hath not it bin hir only triumph?</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe, for MY KING, hath not hee contented himſelfe, to encounter his enemies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12130:13"/>alone, the edge of his ſworde being rebated, the point broken off, his match not fyred, his powder wet, his Ordinance out of carriage, their mouths empty of fire or Salt-Peter, only to fight againſt them with the Armes of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? And where was the field for battail, but in Court of Parlament? And in the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent place of the plain, were all the Monarks, Kings and Princes of Chriſtendome (euen as <hi>Homer</hi> feigned his <hi>Iupiter</hi> on the <hi>Dardanian</hi> mount, where he beheld <hi>Troyan</hi> bandes and ſquadrons of the <hi>Greeks?</hi>) And what was the ſhocke of battell, but the fire diſcouered, the bloud and death of ſome few knowne Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, where Rebellion was taken captiue, to be tied both by hands and feete to the Chaire of King JAMES? Loyalty euermore ſinging with a chearefull voyce, and reſounding in praiſe of his victory, this Triumphant IO, or <hi>Liue King Iames.</hi> That he may liue as trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, euen in <hi>Rome,</hi> as victorious in <hi>Great Brittaine;</hi> as much admired of all the worlde for his Mercie, as feared for his Valour, and cherriſhed and honoured of his people, both for his Piety and Juſtice. For, as <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12130:14"/>and <hi>Knowledge</hi> are written in great Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on his Royall for-head, as knowing how to inſtruct ſtout Rebels, giuing them leſſons of dutie, and apprehenſions, how to liue acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Lawes: ſo (in like maner) may be ſeene ſhining in his Eyes, <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Vertues apt and proper to MY KING.</p>
            <p>And therefore wee ſee him, not running, like <hi>Aratus,</hi> with a drawne ſword in his hand, vpon the Wals of Rome, and to the Tyrants gate, to take reuenge in his iuſt diſpleaſure, but ſeated. Seated in ſigne of Royall power and Soueraignty of his owne right &amp; Iuſtice. Sitting on his <hi>Throne,</hi> in ſigne that <hi>Iehu</hi> ſhall raigne, and that is, according as the Wiſe man approueth it, when he ſaith, <hi>The King that is ſeated vpon his Throne, chaſeth all euill out of his ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, heere doe I ſee my ſelfe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed in ſpirit, and rapt vp to <hi>Heauen,</hi> the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> of the moſt high maieſty of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> the Epicicle moſt eleuate of his Royalty. That is to the <hi>Daix</hi> or State of his <hi>Throne-royall,</hi> where I ſee the God of our Worlde ruling all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12130:14"/>all the Motions, the Aſpects, the influences, &amp; the Coniunctions of all the ſtarres in his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: diſcerning the fixed from erring, and Commets from Plannets; to the end, that all may ſhine the better, and enioy (at length) the Heauen of God, which is the maine end of all his trauailes, and ſhall be the Crowne of his faire Trophees. Hee is ſeated, to bee (as yet) peaceable, the <hi>Sword</hi> hanging but by his ſide, to declare therby, that he would not force the faith, that ſlaughtery, butchery, and all their maſſacres (with the <hi>Phalarian</hi> and <hi>Neronian</hi> torments) are to him moſt horrid and hateful, and that their foule treaſon hath but onely drawne out of his breaſt, a very ſmall ſpark of Diuine fire. Finally, that he hath not cauſed Scaffolds, Jibbets, and Helles to be erected, to handle and puniſh Traitors, according vnto their merits.</p>
            <p>To how many hath hee giuen pardon, as that graue and ſweete Authour of <hi>Tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Torti</hi> (as truely as learnedly) teſtifieth vnto vs? Was there euer any Prince more forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of wrongs, and more apt to remit iniuries
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12130:15"/>done againſt him, then his Maieſty, euen then when he might be very eaſily reuenged? How many Actes of Parliament, full of benignitie, clemency and kindneſſe, hath hee ſet toorth ſince his happy comming to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> euen towards his very enimies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? which is the onely reaſon, that his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects both loue and obey him the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and that ſtraungers ought to bee the more reſpectiue of him.</p>
            <p>For my ſelfe, J may ſay, that (by good right) of him, which the <hi>Romaine</hi> Orator did of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar. Hee is a great Iuſticer, Vpright, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall &amp; true: But in all his vertues, there is none more Great, more Excellent, or more commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then is his Clemency and Benignity.</hi> I ſpeake not this as a Learner, or beeing Tutored thereto; but out of knowledge and good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and as one willing with poore <hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> to ſet a hand to helpe the Arke, whereof J feared the falling. And if I haue done it with out any great paine, yet am I glad that it hath returned me no danger, and ſo long as I ſhall haue any iot of life in mee, I will publiſh eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12130:15"/>where, and ſing in heart, though it bee to my ſelfe;</p>
            <q>
               <l>En tibi praepetibus foelix victoria pennis</l>
               <l>Quae volat, &amp; laet am adducit Clementiapacem,</l>
               <l>Vnde ſalus populis te Rege Iacobe beatis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But fearing the like inconuenience, as that which happened vnto the High-Prieſt <hi>Cecilius Metellus,</hi> for hauing dared to be ſo bold, as to put his hand neere to the Statue of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Pallas:</hi> I am conſtrained to turne my ſight from the faire <hi>Eye</hi> of the Worlde. His Beams do force me to kiſſe the very liddes of thoſe eyes, euen as the perfection and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of his other <hi>Viſible parts,</hi> do reſtraine my tongue, from deliuering the miſticall and Phyſiognomicall ſence of euery one of them. In like maner it was neuer mine intention, to note al the Anatomical conſiderations of his Imperial Body, or to pierce any further, then vnto the ſubtiltie of our owne reach and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion: which dooth ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent it ſelfe, to referre all the functions of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12130:16"/>his parts, to the apparent appearance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to erect a Triumph, not onely fully rich, but alſo morral, to following poſterity.</p>
            <p>We will beginne with his Crowne, which is the Ornament for the <hi>Head,</hi> the chiefeſt member, and that which is moſt honourable of all the body; euen that part, wherein are compoſed al the principal inſtruments of life, by the perfection of numbers. This rich chief part is crowned, to the end, that his enemies beholding the ſame, ſhould enter into the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of <hi>Caſſander</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who hauing founde the Statue of <hi>Alexander,</hi> entred into ſuch a fear, that he trembled at the verie ſight thereof. And to let bee ſeene, that meere glory hath defended him from his greateſt aduerſaries: they ſhoulde bring him no ſuch fraile Crownes, wherewith (in elder times) they were wont to honor the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in the <hi>Olympian, Pythian, Iſmyan,</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean,</hi> games; but that duety which ſhineth in heauen, and can neuer bee withered, becauſe it was firſt wrought and wouen with the verie fingers of the ſonne of God himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12130:16"/>
            <p>It is a Crown of <hi>Gold,</hi> enriched with Pearls and precious Stones. Of <hi>Gold,</hi> which reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the heart, healeth all putride Vlcers, Woolfes, or rotted corruption. To declare thereby, that this King ſhall beare the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Balme, the Cataplaſme and Seare-cloath to heale vlcered hearts and conſciences, euen thoſe which are moſt fired and cauthorized, thereby to bring the new birth againe of the former Golden dayes of <hi>Saturne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pearles</hi> are the Hieroglyphickes of his ſoules immaculate whiteneſſe or integrity, &amp; do teſtifie vnto the whole worlde, that hee is <hi>Protector of Innocency and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Diamonds</hi> do ſhine, and deliuer a clear white luſter, which cheareth the eye. The <hi>Rubies</hi> do dart foorth to ſight very ſtraunge flaming beams, which may offend ſome (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) more then they pleaſe. Theſe are the two moſt precious Stones aboue all other, the Symboles or Creeds of our Churches. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bite or cut the Diamond, but the Diamond it ſelfe; neither can we ſhape or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure any thing elſe therby, of any indamage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or hurt towards vs, but it muſt come by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12130:17"/>our owne ſelues. The <hi>Diamond</hi> is inuulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and not to be bruiſed by hammers on the Anuile: but wil enter farre into the <hi>Ruby,</hi> who is ſubiect to be wrought therewith, penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, cut, carued, or imprinted thereon, in whatſoeuer a man pleaſeth, euen as our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeſe worketh the like effectes in vnbeleeuing harts, which they may very aptly ſignifie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sphear-like</hi> forme of his Crowne doth denote the euen roundneſſe wherein hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth to euery one, as well towards the ſmal as the great, the poore, as the rich. That he is the Common <hi>Father</hi> of all his people, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all his affections in an equall partage, like vnto the <hi>Geometricall</hi> point, which beholdeth all his circumference in one &amp; the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. Anſwerable to the Sun, which ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth equally vpon all: Or as the heart, which furniſheth all the other members with life &amp; heat: Or like vnto the Palme-tree, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributeth his nouriſhment to his leaues and braunches, euen as if it were by iuſt weight &amp; meaſure. Before that Parliament, he conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe to expreſſe vnto the Papiſtes themſelues, rather the power of his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12130:17"/>then the rigour of his Iuſtice. Hee permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all, the free communication of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, as of his Conntreyes ayre, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of his preſence, as the ſweet breath of his fertile kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Booke and the Scepter,</hi> which his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty holdeth in his hands, do repreſent <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Rigor,</hi> which are the two Engines, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all men are drawne to their dutie. For, if Reaſon profit not, recourſe muſt then be had to <hi>Power:</hi> According vnto the example of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles. For they, preſenting peace in all mildneſſe, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all places where they came; ſhooke off (in the ſpirit of Juſtice) the duſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their feet, on them which reſiſted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Saying for reaſon of the firſt; <hi>That be was ſoft and gentle,</hi> and for the ſecond; <hi>That he was vpright or iuſt.</hi> In the firſt; <hi>that he is good &amp; gracious;</hi> in the ſecond, <hi>That he is terrible.</hi> In the firſt, <hi>That hee helpeth the deſolate in hart, &amp; bindeth vp their wounds,</hi> In the ſecond, <hi>That he is Dominus percutiens, a Lord that ſmiteth.</hi> In like maner <hi>Our King, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans leua decus,</hi> wil neuer preſſe with his Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of authority, which he beareth in his right
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12130:18"/>till he may vſe his pen no longer, and that the left hand be wholly deſpiſed. He applyeth not the Raſor to the Canker and <hi>Gangrena</hi> of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,</hi> ſo long as Reaſon, and ſoft and lenitiue remedies may ſerue the turne. Throughout antiquity, <hi>The Scepter</hi> hath bin common to al Kings on the earth. <hi>The Booke</hi> perticularly, and for the excluſion of others, appertaineth to our <hi>Mercuriall Heros,</hi> to enſtruct vs, that of him (properly) ought the double Propheſies bee vnderſtoode. The one of <hi>Cataldus Finius,</hi> which is more then a thouſande yeares ſince: <hi>Iſte ſolus Clare aperiet librum ſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> digito Dei viui, He onely shall euidently open the book, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the finger of the liuing God:</hi> As plainly appeareth by his <hi>Learned Preface.</hi> The other of <hi>Sybilla,</hi> on the deſtruction of Antechriſt: <hi>Miſerum inde tempus quia linum, ipſum perdet,</hi> Miſerable in time ſhall he be, becauſe linnen or a Lyne ſhall deſtroy him. By Linnen his Maieſties Booke is vnderſtoode, the Paper whereof is made of olde decayed linnen: Or elſe the Line or Cord is threatned thereby, to hang him vp, according to the example of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12130:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>His Scepter,</hi> which is in his right hand, is not of wood, made faſt with Iron nayles, as were the ancient Scepters in <hi>Homer</hi> &amp; <hi>Virgil;</hi> nor yet of Juory, ſuch as the Kings of Rome car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and ſent to their Kindred and friendes; nor of <hi>Ebony,</hi> like that of the Jndians: nor of Iron, Copper, or Siluer, but of fine Golde, like that of <hi>Marke Anthonie</hi> in <hi>Florus,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> ſtretched foorth to <hi>Heſter</hi> in the Bible, to ſhew vs, that his is one of the verie Nobleſt Scepters in the world. As <hi>His</hi> length plainly telleth vs, that euen ſo ſhall his power extend it ſelfe, and make it ſelfe to be felt very farre off. It beareth on the top, not any Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, like that of the <hi>Tarquins,</hi> nor a Croſſe, as that did of <hi>Conſtantines:</hi> nor yet a Storke, or the ſtraunge beaſt liuing in the Riuer <hi>Nylns,</hi> called <hi>Hippopotames,</hi> as others haue caried, nor yet a hand like to that of France: But a Lilly or Flowerdeluce, thereby to aſſure vs, that his power and manner of gouernment is full of ſweetneſſe, mildneſſe, and good order.</p>
            <p>The moſt precious garment of his Trophies is a <hi>Royal Mantle</hi> or <hi>Cloake,</hi> the onely ſacred ornament of Kings, for the more ſumptuous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12130:19"/>decking of potent Maieſty, made of <hi>Veluet Azure</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> which are the onely ſightly things that can be vſed in the habit of <hi>princes.</hi> It traineth along vpon the ground after him, to expreſſe the amplitude of his royall benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, being called of God, to couer, not onely the members of his owne eſtate from the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Antichriſt, but likewiſe thoſe people that are ſtrangers, and of other Countries. His colours vnder, are of Scarlet and white, as the Spouſe in the Canticles ſaieth: <hi>That her Beſt-beloued is all white and Vermillion:</hi> white in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, Red &amp; Vermillion in Charity. For euery colour elſe looketh pale and deade, or looſeth his beauty, being neere to theſe, yea, though it be Purple twice dipt in his tincture: As in like maner, the religion of Popery doth (being compared with that which <hi>Our King</hi> embraceth) as being without both ſound and luſter, vaniſhing of it ſelfe away, euen as duſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky clouds do before the beames of the worlds greateſt light. The White of this Mantle roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, is Ermins, which are more perfect in faire luſter, then any other, and thoſe furies do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, not the coldneſſe of his Original coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12130:19"/>(as ſome haue ſcornfully ſaide) but his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and reſolued grauitie, as full of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>As the skin of little blacke ſpots.</hi> Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing vs thereby, that there is nothing ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous, but ſometime it meeteth with ſiniſter accident: as the Ermine, which is white ouer all the body, and yet directly on the top of his tail, hath that ſmal touch or mark of blacknes.</p>
            <p>Vnder this Mantle or Cloake, he weareth the <hi>Palmata Toga,</hi> or <hi>Dalmatian</hi> Veſture, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſome Miniſteriall Office, becauſe the ſleeue reacheth ſo far as the elbow only. The which may teach and perſwade vs, that in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of the Pope, of Anabaptiſts, of al haire-brain'd, mutinous, opiniotiue, and frantique Preachers (whome his Maieſty calleth and vnderſtandeth to bee Puritanes onely) hee is an abſolute Monarch, as well of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, as of the Temporall, euen as in elder times the <hi>Caliphes</hi> were, and that in him is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified the ſaying of the Poet:</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Rex Anyus, Rex idem hominem, Phoebique Sacerdos.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>King <hi>Anyus,</hi> is the ſame man, King, and yet <hi>Apollos</hi> Prieſt.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12130:20"/>
            <p>For Kinges are the Coombes of the Eſtate belonging to God, euen as well as of that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to their kingdomes, and their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is the baſes and foundation, which vpholdeth the Church, in fauour and regard whereof, they were at firſt eſtabliſhed by God, who had neuer created or preſerued the worlde, but for this reſpect onely. They haue like power therin, as <hi>Ioſias</hi> had, and like preheminence as <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who publiſhed himſelf Byſhop of exteriour occaſions. They haue (I ſay) Soueraign iuriſdiction ouer Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, to keepe an eye vpon their Diſcipline, &amp; on the manners or behauiour of the Clergy, to take acknowledgement of their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Which is very eaſie to be proued, as wel by Teſtimonies and ſolid Reaſons, as by the examples and effectes of all moſt venerable Antiquitie.</p>
            <p>Finally, <hi>Our King,</hi> in ſigne of diligence, &amp; that he ſhal very ſhortly triumph in all trueth, Iuſtice, and power, euen as far as that proude <hi>Tarpeiane</hi> Tower, <hi>To kil the Dragon, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the male childe from his throat,</hi> as manifeſtly appeareth by the Angell mounted vppon the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12130:20"/>white horſe, to whom was giuen the Crown of victory: He is circkled with a Girdle of Golde hanging before his breaſt, which is <hi>The Collar of Saint George:</hi> which was not forgotten by the Romaines themſelues of the round Table, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the two Dragons, white and red, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of priſon by <hi>Merlin,</hi> in the time of k. <hi>Vter Pendragon,</hi> father to King <hi>Arthur,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long &amp; deadly fight, the white at length ouercame the red. And now we may ſee a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſurprize them.</p>
            <p>That reiected <hi>Eſau</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Edom</hi>) which ſignified the Red Dragon, that old vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that Tyraunt ouer ſo many Nations, the Pope himſelfe, commeth to the ſuccour of his vanquiſhed Legions, with two Breeues, and a Letter from the Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> which are <hi>Gerions</hi> with three bodies, or <hi>Cerberus</hi> with three heads and throats, caſting fire out at the eyes, the noſe, &amp; the mouth. They would faine faſten on <hi>Our white King Iames,</hi> the Childe of Bleſſedneſſe, euen in his Cabinet, and purſue him thence to his Bed-chamber, in ſeeking to ſet free all his Subiects from their obedience to him: yea, and to turne his very houſholde Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12130:21"/>from their duty: Monarchy being not ſo pleaſing to his taſt, as <hi>Ariſtocratie;</hi> Order, as <hi>Anarchie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold how <hi>Our King</hi> dealt in this manner with them, as others haue done in the like: To day for him, to morrow for them. And their to morrow ſhould haue bin much neerer, if they coulde haue attained to what they pretended. But his Maieſty ſtopt their way with a Mattock and a Wedge, as the <hi>Romaine</hi> Captaine ſaid: or in applying <hi>Triplici nodo Triplicem Cuneum,</hi> in cleauing a Triple knot of Iron, with a Triple wedge of Braſſe; or in cutting <hi>The Gordian knot with the ſword of Alexander.</hi> His Apologie (veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and of good right) ought to be helde for the ſupport, defence, Rampant, and Fortreſſe of all the Kings, Monarkes, and Soueraigne Princes of Chriſtendome, whom at the third voyce of his Triumph, hee awaketh and exhorteth, to maintaine and defend themſelues altogether with him, againſt the attentates and vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Pope, in aduiſing each one of them, according to the rule of reaſon and common fence, grounded vppon cuſtome, and deriued from the Pagan Poet, to learne of the wiſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12130:21"/>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>—Ecquid</l>
               <l>Ad te poſt Paulo ventura periculis ſentis?</l>
               <l>Nam tuares agitur, paries cum proximus ordet,</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>What perilles in ſhort time may come,</l>
               <l>are they vnto thee knowne?</l>
               <l>No, when thy Neighbours houſe doth burne,</l>
               <l>be carefull of thine owne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Monarkes, Soueraignes, Chiefe Iudges of the World, to whom the Iuſtice of heauen hath giuen abſolute power, and Scepters to gouerne the wide Vniuerſe; Earthly Deities, Liuing J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the Eternal, true Lieutenants and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars of God, Fathers of the people, and Tutors of his Church (kneeling on the earth, ſo imitate him in a reſounding Eccho, with her permiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and your owne) waken your ſelues at the voice of My <hi>King.</hi> HOW much more pleaſing ſhould this be vnto you, then that of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, which called them to enter the Liſtes, who preſented themſelues at the Games of <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus?</hi> O Princes, are your heads ſo loaden with vapours, and the Conduites of your vitall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſo ſtopt, that by no agitation or motion, you can bee awaked from this Leaden ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? Doe not you knowe, that the laſt Iudge of the Hebrew people, becauſe hee did ſleepe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12130:22"/>in the lap of his Miſtris, loſt firſt his ſtrength, next his ſight, and ſoone after his life? While you ſleepe ſo profoundly, do not you Dreame what may happen, and much more what hath beene already paſt? Will you ſtill ſlumber, or doe you diſſemble it, when they that ſhoulde watch for you, and feeke to preſerue your Crownes in ſafety, are readyer to bereaue you of them? It is you <hi>Great-Soueraignes,</hi> whom this caſe concerneth. You can be no longer aſſured ſafely, neither in your Pallaces &amp; Cittadels, nor of the faith of your houſhold ſeruants, or thoſe you put moſt truſt in, if this Article may bee graunted to publique murders, and aſſaſinates, (to wit) That they haue power to diſpence, and free your Subiectes from the Oath, whereby they haue vowed faith vnto you, and may cauſe you to be murdered, were it by a <hi>Monke,</hi> and then to Cannonize or glorifie him, when the deede is done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſe then Kings, and prouide for thoſe affayres which the Great God hath put into your hands.</hi> The Church is in tutelage and protection of kings, and you are annointed and Sacred by God, to ſhew by this exterior note, that the care of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12130:22"/>things appertaineth vnto you. Make of vs one heritage, that this ſeame-leſſe Garment of our Lord may no more be torn in peeces. Caſt off the yoak of Antechriſt, who cowardly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Authority to you committed. It is you that haue giuen your power to the beaſt, to fight againſt the Lamb. It is you alſo that ſhold rather hate him, and eate his fleſh. And what hinders you from doing it? Hath not the light of the Goſpell (already) ſufficiently enough diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the frauds of this man of ſinne? The Spirit out of the mouth of Ieſus Chriſt, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed aboundantly in ſo many places, and yet continuing, hath it not already foyled him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the moſt ſignall parts of his Dominion? There is not any Prince or Common-wealth, but is weary to ſee this Tyraunt (faire from all obligation of Lawes, Equity, and Juſtice) to gurmundize and deuoure vp all the Eſtates of Chriſtendome. The Pope ſeemes to ſollicite Heauen and earth, euen to his owne ruine, and Coniures all <hi>Europe</hi> to make but one <hi>Aeſopes</hi> Crow. All the world is in a ſhiuering, ſo highly is it offended at his Tyranies, and deſireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe with vs, but one iuſt Conference, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12130:23"/>which alſo is the aduiſe of <hi>Our wiſe and Learned King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is neceſſary, that a good, free, and lawfull Counſell ſhould bee called and aſſembled, by you Princes and Soueraigne Eſtates, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound all theſe diſſentions and differences in Religion: as being (at all times) the onely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meanes, to aboliſh Schiſmes, diſanull Hereſies, and to reforme whatſoeuer is amiſſe in Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline. This is the onely way, to reſtore the wanderers, to winne their harts more ſenſibly, and to conſolidate the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing members, to the great body of the Church, and to revnite the willes of your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ſcattered into factions. Such ſickly and diſeaſed Spirits, doe require a milde and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cure, the keene edged ſword of the worde is that which pierceth into the Soule, and the Church inſtructeth not to perſecute, but to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh and informe ſuch as are in error. And it ſeemeth that this way is deſired, wiſhed and requeſted by many, who do offer to ſubmitte themſelues, to that which thereby ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, concluded, and ordained.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12130:23"/>
            <p>Such a notable occaſion is not any way to be contemned, <hi>Non oportetſi quod omnibus, votis petendum erat, vltro offertur, faſtidire.</hi> An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all at this time, hauing a <hi>Conſt antine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your ſelues, capable to preſide as the other did in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Aſſemblies, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of whom is able to diſpoſe of differences, to ſoften the ſharpeſt, to reſtore &amp; place peace and concord among all good Fathers, not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate or intereſſed in ſtrange opinions, and to make them happily finiſh ſuch a deſſeign, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your beſt furtherance. If this happen not in our dayes, let vs neuer flatter our ſelues with any humaine hope, of compaſsing it heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Our laſt ankor is caſt, hauing ſuch a Prince, Vertuous, Wiſe, Learned, Eloquent, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, Conquering, Victorious, wel obeyed, Abſolute in his kingdome, and beyond all this, nouriſhed and educated in pietie, and in the true ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>And now ſee him among all other Kings, in his ſecond Triumphall Chariot, like to the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the other beaſts.</p>
            <p>Where wee may ſee this Lyon in the Armes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12130:24"/>of MY KING (which is the note of his ſecond victory) as all they do which behold this <hi>Great Salomon</hi> vpon his Throne, round engirt with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Theſe Images do giue them a ſudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, as appearing terrible and dreadful to them. But when they approach neerer, they ſee that the Lyons are of Golde, and as they mount to the feete of the Prince, the ſame Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do ſerue as a guarde and defence. In like maner ſeemeth it to them, which a farre off do behold the Lyon Rampant of Scotland, that he breatheth forth nothing elſe but puniſhments, death and deſolation: but when they com nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and conſider him aduiſedly, they finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but purity and perfection, which is verie ſolid and moſt pure and perfect Gold. And if they ſhould yet ſtand in neede of the clemency of <hi>My Prince,</hi> this generous Lyon will ſerue them as a prop, ſupply and ſupport thereto.</p>
            <p>It is a Lyon Rampant, to repreſent vnto vs the Maieſty of his Maieſty, who in ſtrength and furie is a true Lyon, when the preſumptuous boldneſſe of men ſhall bee ſuch, as willingly to reiect his clemency; <hi>Leo vngiet, &amp; formidabunt filij maris.</hi> Then the turbulent, traitors, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12130:24"/>powder men, and ſuch like; who are all as Marine-Monſters, and Children of <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> ſhall quake with feare. <hi>Huic Galli terrori non ſunt.</hi> And in trueth, <hi>Hic eſt Leo qui vinciri pernegat,</hi> according to the Miſtery which is on the Med aile of the Duke of <hi>Albania.</hi> For if the Childretn of <hi>Saleucus,</hi> had each of them on his thigh an Anchor imprinted or carractred, as a certaine marke of the line of their extraction; And the race of <hi>Python</hi> of <hi>Niſibis,</hi> had the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion of an Axe on their bodies, which teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the honour of their lineage: Euen ſo, <hi>Our King,</hi> dooth not carry this Lyon onely in his Shield, as for a ſhew, but likewiſe in ſign of his harts generoſity, hath one liuely figured on his bodie, vnder his left pappe, <hi>Ab vtero Matris ſuae,</hi> which is not without a very great miſtery.</p>
            <p>As concerning the <hi>Floures de Lys</hi> or <hi>Lyllies,</hi> which <hi>Charle-Maigne</hi> cauſed to be doone in a double draught about the Scottiſh Eſcutchion, in the time of <hi>Achaius,</hi> the yeare 777. in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall memory of their alliance: it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that they firſt came from heauen. So that all other floures (beeing compared with them) doe appeare no otherwiſe, but euen as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12130:25"/>Thiſtles, Brambles, and Bryers: <hi>Sicut Lilium inter ſpinas, ita Amica mea inter Filias;</hi> Like as a Lilly among the Thorns, ſo is my Loue among the Daughters (ſaide Jeſus Chriſt) in ſpeaking of his Church. Whereupon, ſome Doctours, very curious and contemplatiue, haue noted three eſpeciall things in this faire and Celeſtiall Flower (to wit;) his purity and whiteneſſe, his admirable ſweet ſauour, and his phiſical vertue againſt al burnings. And by his growing amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thornes, they ſignified idolatries, impieties, and hereſies, among which pure and vnſpotted do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin ſhall alwaies ſhine moſt brightly. The <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines</hi> alſo, they found out infinit goodly &amp; rare Miſteries, vpon the inſcription of the Pſalme, where it is ſaide; <hi>Ad victoriam Lilijs.</hi> And the Naturaliſts do affirme, that there is an oyle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the Lilly, able to cure the Palſie, the head ache, and deafeneſſe in the eares; in ſigne, that the Writings of <hi>Our King</hi> ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſerue, to heale the ſickeneſſe of ſpirit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Church of God to her firſt ſtrength and conualeſcence.</p>
            <p>Nor was it enough, that this Lilly of Alliance ſhould bee a Lilly onely, and no more then a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12130:25"/>Lilly, but that it ſhould alſo haue the vertue and property, which Nature had beſtowed vppon the Lilly. And therefore he willed withall, that this Lilly ſhould bee of Golde, in a double draught: to declare thereby, that the vertues of our Kings, ſhould exceed them of other Kings in quality; yea, euen in quantity, according as Gold is the moſt precious thing among all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate creatures. He placed them alſo round about his Armes, in ſigne of the loude terrour which they had giuen, and ſhall yet giue (if it pleaſe God) as well ouer the whole great conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as in their owne little worlde, made, and made perfect, by the coniunction of thoſe <hi>three Leopards with that Lyon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This new Alliance, in paſsing the Spunge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes or aboue the Table of our fatall diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hath vnited our <hi>Lyon Rampant,</hi> with the 3. Leopardes, three <hi>Floured de Luce</hi> or Lillies of England, and the <hi>Harpe</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the end, they might be eight in all, as they of elder times were wont to ſay, namely, <hi>perfect.</hi> Becauſe none can goe any further then this, when a number or figure is come vnto his Triple dimenſion of length, bredth, and depth. According to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12130:26"/>
               <hi>Pythagorians,</hi> it is the number of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> becauſe that firſt of all it reſulteth it ſelfe into numbers of paire-like-parity, deuiding equally al things. By meanes whereof, it is iuſtly attributed vnto Ieſus Chriſt, who is onely iuſt.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Cui tria ſunt octo, tu me ſeruabis vt opto</l>
               <l>Ne voret innumerus, cui tria ſex numerus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which was likewiſe foretold by <hi>Sybilla,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our Sauiour.</p>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>Although the number be one eight,</l>
               <l>and eight tens in account!</l>
               <l>Yet to eight hundred ſhall his name,</l>
               <l>in valuation mount.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Eight is like the <hi>Cube,</hi> which ſignifieth firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ſtability, in that it turneth his face to all, and turning downe from aboue, commeth vnderneath, yet is it euermore firmely ſeated, and in one and the ſame forme. It is alſo a ſolid body, which hath his dimenſions and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by reaſon of his foure direct or right An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, for better ſeating and making himſelfe firme: which rendring it ſo maruailouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and miſticall, doth therby the better repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him vnto vs, who by his power hath reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12130:26"/>&amp; reconfirmed the eſtate of mankinde. Eight, compoſed of this Royall vnity of <hi>Our Lyon,</hi> and of the <hi>English Septeuery,</hi> doth make vp the Armories perfect in all their meaſures: alſo by this fair mixture of numbers, that ſweet harmony is made, which entertaineth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the whole kingdom in good peace and quietneſſe.</p>
            <p>And not to diſpute heere, concerning the <hi>Three Leopards, the three Floures de luces, &amp; the Harpe,</hi> which being ſeuerally ioyned with the Lyon, doe make fiue, the Symbole or ſigne of health or ſafety: which number, among al them that are not paires, do appeare to bee the moſt nuptiall, and beſt beſeeming mariage. Becauſe three is the firſt, no-paire, &amp; two the firſt paire, and fiue is compoſed of theſe two, as both of male and female, which ſheweth vnto vs, that <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> are in ſuch ſort marryed together at this inſtant, by mutuall loue in a true, pure, and ſincere Religion, liuing alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one faith, vnder one King and Law, as they are neuer heereafter to bee ſundred or deuided.</p>
            <p>The Teruary number, or of three, is of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12130:27"/>Leopardes, Guardians of our <hi>Microcoſmns</hi> or little world (not of great Maſties or Dogges, not of Tigers and Draggons, preſeruers of the <hi>Heſperides</hi> Apples) which do expreſſe vnto vs, that the vertues and power of <hi>Our King,</hi> is not onely to cleanſe the world of all Idolatry, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Error, and ignorance: but alſo of worldly knowledge, of the wiſedom of <hi>Hagars</hi> children, of the ſapience of <hi>Babilon,</hi> of political prudence, which imployes it ſelfe to the acquiſition and maintenance of dignities, riches, and his owne caſe, without regard of piety or Religion. <hi>The King,</hi> by the very ſweetueſſe of his breath, ſhal draw the Leopardes themſelues to him, they hauing the pawes of the Lyon, or the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a Chriſtian, and lay holde on the Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is Hereſie by his ſpottes or blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, becauſe ſhee is the Mother and Nurſe to many meruailes.</p>
            <p>Theſe are true <hi>Candiots, Chameleons,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> who beleeue not in God, but by an inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory or Regiſter, who acknowledge no other Diuinity, then that which is called State, who worſhippe not (as the Emperour <hi>Iouinian,</hi> and <hi>Themiſtius</hi> the Phyloſopher ſayd) but the ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12130:27"/>Purple of Kinges onely, without Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without any taſt or feeling of a ſecond life, or feare of a ſecond death: little caring for any thing, but greatneſſe in the worlde, which ſerues them for Religion, as fitly, as the Buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins of <hi>Theramines,</hi> would do for walking.</p>
            <p>Behold, how like another <hi>Orpheus, Amphion,</hi> and <hi>Arion,</hi> he draweth to the true knowledge of God, very ſaluage Beaſts, Forreſts, Trees, and Stones, by the ſweet Harmony of his Harp: the moſt fierce and wilde, the moſt ſtupid and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenced, the moſt brutiſh and voluptuous, are changed and ciuilized by the delectable ſound of his Muſicke. The which may tranſport and rauiſh our cares, at his mellodious touchinges and concordes, and not tickle them with any delicate noyſe, tending vnto voluptuous and ſenſuall pleaſure: but rather ſuch, as (by well tempered proportions) are able to reduce all extrauagant rudeneſſe, and circuites of our ſoules, though they had wandered from the right way, to the true path of dutie, and ſettle all thoughts in ſuch a harmony, as is moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto them. For this is that Ladie indeede (ſaith <hi>Zoroaſtres</hi>) which doth make a man leap
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12130:28"/>with ioy, when he feeleth in himſelfe an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, like a ſweet conſort of Muſicke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he is admitted with God and his Angels. But, according to <hi>Proclus,</hi> ſo ſoone as hee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſhe abſenteth her ſelfe, and he remain eth depriued of her company. Heereupon, the euill Spirit, or proud <hi>Demon</hi> (in the iudgement and ſaying of the <hi>Cabaliſts</hi>) in his fall, loſt wholly the Muſicall harmony which was in him.</p>
            <p>In like manner, there are no ſoules wel born, but in them this harmony may haue place (ſo ſaith <hi>Pyndarus</hi>) and that the bad ſpirits cannot endure a ſweete concording Muſicke, becauſe it is quite contrary to their diſproportioned na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. This may bee witneſſed by <hi>Saule</hi> King of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when hee was poſſeſſed with the euill Spirit, <hi>Dauid</hi> by the ſound of his Harpe, compelled him to depart from the King, or at the leaſt to let him be quiet. <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Boetius</hi> recordeth, I knowe not by what Mellody, but by a Muſicall Ayre thereto apt and proper, brought a young man into his perfect ſences, that had bin before mad and diſtracted. The like we read of <hi>Terpander, Arion, Iſmenius</hi> and <hi>Linus,</hi> Muſicians of <hi>Thebes,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12130:28"/>who thus reduced very many bad diſtempered and moſt peruerſe people into the right way of vertue. It is likewiſe ſaid, that <hi>Thales</hi> the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſian,</hi> appeaſed the ciuil diſſentions among the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> by the ſweete mellody of his Harpe onely.</p>
            <p>From whence, wee may collect the maruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous effects of Muſick by Inſtruments, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by acknowledge, that it is able (very extreamly) to excite humain affections, as being ful of high and hidden miſteries, if we may giue credit to the <hi>Hebrewes Cabala,</hi> and the very learnedſt <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines.</hi> For this Harpe of MY KING is made in a triangle, hauing ten ſtrings, which being tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched aboue, doe reſound beneath, and deliuer ſuch an acceptable mellody, as it pierceth all the Celeſtiall Spheares, euen by ſanctified de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, conceiued to the honour of God, and it trauerſeth all Countries of the whole world, for the defence and ſupport of all Kinges, Princes, and Commonweales of Chriſtendome. Such are the accents of this miſticall ſimphony, and the lofty tunes of the <hi>Diapenthes, Diateſſarons,</hi> and <hi>Diapaſons</hi> of our <hi>Royall Harpe.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12130:29"/>
            <q>
               <l>Beſtirre ye euerie faithfull hart,</l>
               <l>To the Harpes Muſicke beare apart,</l>
               <l>Hanging in his Silken twine,</l>
               <l>Sing his praiſe that is Diuine.</l>
               <l>With Lutes and Organes mellodie,</l>
               <l>And holy Songs ſweete Harmonie:</l>
               <l>All laud his name continually.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Ad Triarios ventumeſt,</hi> and vnto the third voice of his Triumph, which prepareth the Trophees of out <hi>Iacob,</hi> for his victory ouer <hi>Gog,</hi> or the hidden and couert <hi>Eſau,</hi> for all <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> and Monſters mentioned, neither could, nor can do any thing (God bee thanked) with their overt power, againſt his ſacred perſon. Heere we muſt looke for <hi>Hags, Goblins, Deuils, Night-walkers</hi> (as <hi>Plancus</hi> ſaide againſt <hi>Pollio</hi>) armed, with not viſible weapons, but with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous thoughts, lying tongues, and pennes more daungerous, then the fire, then the Iron barres, or then the barrels of Gun-powder, to tax him in his <hi>Name and Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One is a <hi>Critick Anonymus,</hi> and inſenſed Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, hauing the eyes of his vnderſtanding ſo masked or hudwincked, that he could no more ſee the Author of the <hi>Royall Apollogie,</hi> then hee ſaw his Right to the Crowne of England. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is a wry-treading <hi>Tortus,</hi> ſo Crooked in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12130:29"/>heart, and Lame in ſpirit, that he cannot walke vpright or directly in his Doctrine. And both of them <hi>Andabates,</hi> or purblinde Fencers, who, for the vglineſſe and deformity of their ſoules, are glad to hide themſelues vnder the cloake of thoſe borrowed falſe names: to the end, that they may beſtow their blowes where beſt they pleaſe, lying impudently, and belying as well the Gods, as men. And becauſe his maieſty do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fight but with <hi>Chimaeraes</hi> and ſhadowes, he breaks through all the daunger of their mallice, becauſe hee can no neerer grapple with them: for the firſt hath as yet eſcaped (for ſome time) the hands of Juſtice, and the Hangmans halter.</p>
            <p>Theſe wicked and deteſtable men, to whom nothing is deare, prouided, that it may do hurt to ſuch as they maligne and malice, do inuent crimes, forge offences, hurle <hi>Pelion</hi> vpon <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> to ouerthrow the Gods: but it is an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maxime, that a lye liuing but an houre one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may yet beget ſome friuolous effect, and ſo they feare not, but woulde faine perſwade the people, that the King is not the Author of the Booke, and therefore they repay him with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, inſtead of honeſt Reaſons.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:12130:30"/>
            <p>But the modeſty of his Maieſty, ſcorning horſe-play, to ſtrike with his heels, like the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fencer <hi>Cteſiphon,</hi> was content to auouch the Booke by his learned Monitory Preface, which is not onely an aunſwere to ſuch baſe fellowes, but alſo written in iuſt contempt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he imitateth <hi>Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Lucan,</hi> who to commit nothing vnbeſeeming the greatneſſe of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and renowne of his Armies, did the like to Cowardly <hi>Metellus,</hi> beeing deſperate of his glorie, lying then at the ſtake to be foyled.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Vanam ſpem mortis honeſtae</l>
               <l>Concipis, haud (inquit) iugulo ſe polluet iſte</l>
               <l>Noſtra Metelle manus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Neuer did he triumph with greater pompe, then in refuſing this fight, euen as did <hi>Fabius Maximns,</hi> in refuſing to triumph. For the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and falſe calumnies of both theſe Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, are ſo notorious through the world, as ther is no man, who hearing the children of <hi>Beliall</hi> diſgorge their blaſphemies, but doth know, &amp; will confeſſe it openly, yea, and loud enough to bee heard: that it is the naturall property of them, who (after they haue beene ſo long time nouriſhed in blaſpheming againſt GOD) doe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12130:30"/>do thinke they may be iuſtly diſpenſed withall, in rayling, lying, and ſpeaking falſely of their Princes.</p>
            <p>Who could beleeue, that in <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> they had an <hi>Harpocrates,</hi> one of the <hi>Indian Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> or a King with a <hi>Shut-mouth,</hi> that could not make anſwere to two Breeue of the Pope, and to a Letter ſent from a Cardinall? Had not his ſilence in this caſe ſeemed as little important, as if he had giuen conſent thereto? And coulde any thinke him ſo weake in wiſedom, as to ſay with the <hi>Romain</hi> Emperor, <hi>would God I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer learned the firſt Elements of Letters,</hi> when no Queſtion is to be made, but that hee is able to warrant himſelfe (with his pen onely) againſt the Tyranies of Antichriſt? Not any (I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded) could be ſo idely conceited.</p>
            <p>Let vs then chearefully auouch it, and in the fauour of his Triumph, engraue in great letters on the baſes of this ſtatue, the ſecret ſence which is hidden in his Armes, euen in the Frontiſpice of his Apology, which is, <hi>Iames Triumphant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>That as in all parts by Gods grace,</l>
               <l>is ſpread his Royall Name:</l>
               <l>So may the worlds remoteſt Lands,</l>
               <l>both know, and ſpeake his fame.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12130:31"/>
            <p>To the end, that theſe <hi>Ground Moles,</hi> who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſawe their own eimpudence, may ſcent or ſmell it out by thoſe goodly Carracters. And if to them it may ſeeme inopinate (as I beleeue it) let them then take-occaſion to conſider wel, yea and weigh what they promiſe or portend, as in an interlaced miſticall Cipher.</p>
            <p>The Authour is <hi>Iames</hi> the <hi>Great Monark</hi> the <hi>Protectour</hi> and <hi>Propagator</hi> of the <hi>Faith,</hi> the <hi>Rampart</hi> of Chriſtendome, the <hi>Fort</hi> and <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke</hi> of the Church, the <hi>Succour</hi> of true <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> the <hi>Enemy</hi> of <hi>Heretiques,</hi> the <hi>Terrour</hi> of <hi>Infidels,</hi> the <hi>Support</hi> of the <hi>Afflicted,</hi> the <hi>Tamer</hi> of <hi>Monſters,</hi> the <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> and the <hi>Bleſsing of his time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which the very blindeſt will bee enforced to confeſſe, conſidering the aſsiſtaunce of God in all his actions, and how he hath preſerued him from ſo many dangers, euen by extraordinarie maruels: wherefore (by good right) he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to be accounted, <hi>The King of wonders,</hi> or <hi>The wonder of kings, The Miracle of the ages pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; to come.</hi> For my ſelfe, when I come to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider by what meanes he hath bin hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, I am euen ſwallowed vp in admiration,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12130:31"/>and the more contradictions and aſſaults J find by ſo many <hi>Eſaus,</hi> the more I reuerence thoſe high conditions wherunto God hath brought him: for he could not come into the world, but through the danger of blowes, euen amongeſt the horrors of blood &amp; death. As we plainly ſee, that the Roſe cannot be gathred without prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; to giue the greater ſound to his vertues, he was borne to wade through diuers dangers.</p>
            <p>For, to let ſleepe in ſilence that wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and the very <hi>Non-pareile</hi> offer that euer was aduentured, euen to ſmite him quite tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the heart, in the womb of the late <hi>Queen</hi> his <hi>Mother</hi> of happy memory, foure monethes before he ſaw the light of this world: it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that it could not ſo haue happened, but by the very ſpeciall prouidence of God, &amp; to make the whole vniuerſe ſtand amazed therat, as the ſpectator of our bloudieſt Tragedies. So in his very birth likewiſe, he held <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heele, &amp; in his Cradle (in imitation of great <hi>Hercules</hi>) he ſmothered &amp; ſtrangled great ſtore of Serpents.</p>
            <p>In the tendereſt of his youth, his enimies, who had no aſſured ſubiect wherein to lodge their ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but in the Mazer or cup of his deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12130:32"/>they feared not to attempt by open force. But heauen being much ſtronger then the poiſon, diſsipated and quailed all their diſſeignes. Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes in very deede, ouer-bold to ſome, to ſee them ſo highly pearched or placed in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, whoſe execution drew on ſo many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and calamities in our Countrey, as I am aſhamed to ſpeak it, except it be to expreſſe the great bleſsings of God towards our <hi>Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who as he went to <hi>Padan-baran,</hi> or towards <hi>Denmarke,</hi> to take a wife in the Royal houſe of the King, how cruelly was he aſſayled by furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Medeaes,</hi> and his owne chiefe Ship foulded vp in ſtearne Tempeſts? Contrary Windes did afflict it, beate and driue it euery where, they excited and blew the Waues, which ſwelled, foamed, roared, and gaped with open mouths to ſwallow him. And as the winds wraſtled on either ſide, againſt the Maſt, the ſayles, and the maine yard, behold, euen in labouring (with al their might) to deuoure him, they proued the cauſe of his happy eſcape, and with full ſayles (through all the ſtormes) brought him to Port <hi>Laetus,</hi> in which place, al <hi>Scotland</hi> at his return, welcommed him with ſingular ioyfulneſſe.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12130:32"/>Euen as the whole Iſle receiued <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, at his home returne from ſtrange wars, by deliuering him theſe words in the mouth of <hi>Optatianus Porphyrius.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Omnis ab Arctois plaga finibus horrida Cauro</l>
               <l>Pacis amat cana &amp; comperta perennia iura</l>
               <l>Et tibi fida tuis ſemper benè militat armis</l>
               <l>Réſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gerit virtute tuas, populóſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> feroces</l>
               <l>Propellit, cedít<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lubens tibi debita rata</l>
               <l>Et tua victores ſors accipit hinc tibi fortes</l>
               <l>Te<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Duce inuictae attollant ſigne cohortes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Congratulating alſo the fortunate comming of the Queene, by this diſcourſe in effect and affection, but in wordes much better ſhaped &amp; couched.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MAgnificent</hi> &amp; <hi>Great Princeſſe,</hi> Sacred blood of the <hi>Danes,</hi> Race Royall, Wife, Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; Siſter to a King? If I ſhould receiue into my Ports, and on my ſhores, the <hi>Great Iuno</hi> of <hi>Candy,</hi> the Daughter of old <hi>Saturne,</hi> the Wife &amp; Siſter of <hi>Iupiter</hi> of <hi>Creet;</hi> Jf I ſhould receiue <hi>Palas</hi> herſelfe, <hi>Minerua</hi> her ſelfe, the <hi>Great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miramis,</hi> the Stately <hi>Cleopatra<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the Empreſſe <hi>Zenobia:</hi> If I ſhould receiue euen hir, that wears at this day the Crowne of the <hi>Romain Empire,</hi> the <hi>Empire</hi> of the Eaſt, the Kingdomes of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12130:33"/>
               <hi>Spaine,</hi> of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> of <hi>Egipt,</hi> of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iohn,</hi> and all that which the <hi>Great Signeur</hi> or <hi>Turke</hi> hath, and may haue for his Queene, yet could I not receiue a more great Princeſſe then you MADAME, for Royalty of bloode, Luſter of <hi>Nobility,</hi> and Nobleneſſe of ſo aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent a <hi>Family,</hi> neither could I receiue a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe more ſplendant in Beauty, and all good <hi>Graces.</hi> Come then <hi>Great Queene,</hi> &amp; by your comming make mee moſt happy. <hi>Happy</hi> ſhall you long time be in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and for the greater height of your <hi>Glorie,</hi> bee you alſo a happy <hi>Mother of Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſhe ſhall be (God aſsiſting) as alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (by his eſpeciall bleſsing, and more then particuler fauour) <hi>her Maieſty</hi> hath had <hi>My Lord</hi> the Prince of <hi>VVales, My Lord</hi> the <hi>Duke of Yorke,</hi> and the <hi>Lady Elizabeth</hi> their Siſter, and thereby not only makes <hi>Scotland</hi> happy, but al <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> whereon dependeth their peace and freedom from ſtrife (euen as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the <hi>Halcions</hi> do make the Sea calme, &amp; commodious for Nauigation) which wanting before in that Empires felicity, makes it now an Empire abounding in felicity. Shee hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12130:33"/>our <hi>Delos,</hi> and hath ſet vs aboue the winds, as ſafe ſheltred from all ſtormes, by the firme aſſurances of ſo faire a ſucceſsion: &amp; this ſufficeth not only for the coniunction &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of this Eſtate, but alſo for the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereof. Wherefore, no kingdome in the worlde is there, which hath more occaſion to glad it ſelfe in her Queene, then <hi>Great Brittain</hi> in her Gracious <hi>Queene,</hi> or in the faire and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady <hi>Anne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, <hi>Our King,</hi> after this voyage of his, was yet againe purſued by tumultuous Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: but beholde, how (our <hi>Vliſses</hi>) eſcaped the cruelty of <hi>Polyphemus.</hi> I doe not meane that which was done (in the ſilence of a mournefull night) at the Abbey of Saint <hi>Croſſe,</hi> albeit the noiſe therof redounded euen into the chamber of his Maieſty (the <hi>Amneſtia</hi> &amp; law of Obliuion, hauing ſent ſome part to death &amp; the graue, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other part to the gallowes &amp; bellies of Crowes, &amp; the laſt to the curſe of al coragious ſpirits) but J would ſpeake of the inhumanity of thoſe two Brethren, who violated the laws of Hoſpitality, vpon the perſon of their Prince and Father. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, I meane the Treaſon of thoſe two <hi>Eſaues,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:12130:34"/>that made tender of preſents to <hi>Our Iacob,</hi> thoſe two <hi>Athletes</hi> and daungerous <hi>Antees,</hi> that wraſtled with him in the mid-day time, in cloſe field, with feete lifted vp, and armes outſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, to bind and beare him to ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mercie: where he being alone, without any helpe but God onely (who neuer forſooke him) laboured them out of breath. Whereby his very enemies are conſtrained to confeſſe, that hee is verily elected of God, and for the glory of his name.</p>
            <p>In like manner, As he went towards his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> to enioy the right of his firſt begetting, it ſeemes the like ſhould haue been done in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> All <hi>Europe</hi> prepared their eyes, to ſee the fall of that ſtately Monarchy, the greatneſſe wherof had compaſſed the whole Globe of the earth. All the world ran to the bruiſing of that mighty Ship, when it pleaſed God to look vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs with the eye of his mercy, and defend vs from that fall, by his moſt powerfull Arme. Whereby hee plainly declared to all the earth, that he is the preſeruer of Kings, the God <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telarie</hi> of kingdoms, and the Patron of al Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Eſtates. He hath thereby alſo giuen a leſſon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12130:34"/>to all Kings and Princes of the world, that their raigning is by him onely, and that it is an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much boldneſſe in any, as ſhall ſeeke to exalt himſelfe, or grow great, againſt his ordinance and expreſſe commandement.</p>
            <p>But it is nothing to ſee him Monarke of the Engliſh, as alſo endued with ſuch authority &amp; power, except we vnderſtand withall, by what means it was thus prouided, for that is it, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bleſsing and wonderfull worke of God towards him is to be diſcerned.</p>
            <p>For (in the Papiſtes opinion) the Lawes, the Eſtates, the Counſell, the Citties, the Country, the great, the ſmall, the rich, the poore, the young, the old, and all ſexes ſhould haue vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally refuſed him, and denied him his right: But heerein they were deceiued, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple better aduiſed, as being more wiſely expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in affairs of the world. They, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his iuſt merit, and being effectually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, in the will and affection of good aged <hi>Rebecca,</hi> his Mother <hi>Hereditatis,</hi> they cauſed his ſweet ſmelling ſauour to bee felt of all, and (by their good example) reformed the errour of diuers other. So that all vnanimately or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12130:35"/>with one conſent, were in duty compelled to reſpect him, and proſtrate themſelues before his Royall Maieſty. The Clergy (whom Pope and Papiſtes would haue had to doubt) moſt earneſtly deſired him; the Nobility, that ſhuld haue left him, chearefully elected him; Iuſtice, who ſhould haue left him, intirely imbraceth him; the people, who ſhould haue fled from him, do all ſeeke after him: &amp; we may well ſay, that he hath bin the vowes, the deſire and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall wiſh of the whole kingdom, yea, in ſuch maner, that (in deſpight of Popiſh malice) Our King, is as a fable reduced into an hiſtorie, <hi>Qui tanquam lapis quem rebrobanerunt, factus eſt caput anguli.</hi> They that thoght to ſee him at their feet, do acknowledge him to be their head, &amp; they to whom he was as nothing, at this day do loue &amp; honor him for their king. A wonderful work wrought by the prouidence of God, who in his ſtrict and ſecret counſel, kept it hid for a day, to publiſh &amp; propoſe it then to mankind for euer, and againſt the opinion of ſome enuious Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, to make him King of the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>O happy Engliſh, that haue no more women and children for your King, but a King full of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12130:35"/>ſtrength, a king participating the verdure of his youth, and ful ripeneſſe of his age. O moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, to haue a King that loues you more then himſelfe, and deſireth not to liue, but for your preſeruation. O more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thrice happy, to haue a King among your ſelues, who is natural vnto you who commeth not to raign, by the furies of a mutinous multitude, nor by the fauours of a blind fold Fortune, but by the bleſsing of <hi>God,</hi> and right of birth, as wel by the Fathers ſide, as the Mothers. To abreuiate theſe maruayles, there is no man ignorant, but he wel knoweth; that this kingdome had bin ſwallowed vp in an hideous <hi>Chaos,</hi> the fift day of Nouember, 1605. if the Diuine goodneſſe had not appeared (in ſuch a need) to this <hi>Great King,</hi> euen like a new Starre at the breake of day, to ſcatter the lateſt night that came to ouer-whelme vs. In which wonderfull deliuerance, he hath euidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto vs, that he will haue his Maieſty to liue and flouriſh more then euer heeretofore: becauſe he drew him out of this bottomeleſſe pit, by raiſing vs ſuch ſuccour, withour which he had vndoubtedly bin expired, by ſuch cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as the like were neuer heard of.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12130:32"/>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animus meminiſſe borret Luctuque refugit.</q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">The heart abhorres remembrance, tears flye from it.</q>
            <p>Thus we ſee, that the Authour of the Booke, was fore-appointed of God by his name and perſon, as long ſince, was <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whom he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw, prouided and called by his name, two hundred yeares before hee was borne, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him againſt Kings and Nations, enemies to his word and people. That verily, and in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, by all the periods and paralelles of his life, this is <hi>Iacob,</hi> according to the Hebrewes, and <hi>Iames</hi> in <hi>Scottish,</hi> the <hi>Pentaphyllon,</hi> or the name of fiue Letters, bearing the worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The <hi>Pentagon,</hi> in former time Myſteriouſly reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to King <hi>Antiochus,</hi> ſur-named the Sauiour, for the ſauing and conſeruation of his people. That it is he, <hi>Among the ten Kings,</hi> as the great finger among the reſt, as the Sun amongſt the fiue male Planets; as hearing, among the fiue Sences, and among the fine woundes, that of the heart, to ſaue and preſerue vs That it is he, who ſhewes vs Antichriſt, by the fiue markes of the Apocalypſe: Firſt, <hi>That be is an Idolater,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>a Murderer,</hi> thirdly, an <hi>Empoyſoner,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:12130:36"/>fourthly, <hi>a whore,</hi> fiftly, <hi>a Thiefe:</hi> And that it is hee, who ſhall at length Triumph ouer Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fift, becauſe that the ſundry accidents of men, of States, and of affaires, do rowle or giue by the number quaternary, or of four, and then reſt themſelues vpon the fift, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted by the firſt Letter of the Hebrew Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet (HE) redoubled to the great Tetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grammaton IEHOVA, which afterwarde in the Law of Grace, was amplified to a quina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or number of fiue, IESVS. And the ſame is iudged alſo, by the ſeauen Letters, or Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall number of his name, in Greeke, Latine, and French, whereby likewiſe is made &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly comes their mutations and renewings. It is the holy number, &amp; it ſignifieth all plenitude and perfection: as contrariwiſe, the number of two (whereof is <hi>Papa,</hi> the name of his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the moſt common and generally knowne) is an Hierogliphicke of filthineſſe, of wickednes, and of the diuine vengeance, as all our Doctors haue obſerued. In <hi>Papa,</hi> there is nothing elſe but <hi>P. A.</hi> doubled into two Syllables, after the ſame manner as the <hi>Pythagorians</hi> ſignifyed the Deuill. Alſo it is ſaide, that <hi>The Beaſt shal ſpeak
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12130:37"/>like the Dragon,</hi> and that Antichriſt, ſhal come in the efficacy of Sathan. According vnto the Nature of Numbers, the Septenary or that of ſeauen, whereof is <hi>Iacobus,</hi> is the number firſt ſacred and hallowed by the Creator, and it is taken for a ſigne of his Diuine reſt: the <hi>Binary</hi> or that of two, is the firſt number that deuides or withdrawes it ſelfe from the vnity, and from his beginning. Moreouer, in all the daies of the creation, the Scripture ſaith, <hi>And God ſaw that it was good,</hi> except the ſecond onely: not as ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng, that what he had created on that day was not good; but to ſet a ſecret mark theron, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the numbers ſignification. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Noah</hi> ſent into the Ark, <hi>The cleave creatures by ſeauen and ſeauen, and the vncleane by two and two. Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſsyrian</hi> receiued commaund from <hi>Elyſeus,</hi> to go waſh himſelfe ſeauen times in <hi>Iordain,</hi> to be healed of his leproſie. But two Angels were ſent to conſume <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrba;</hi> &amp; two molten Calues were prouided, to be the firſt Idols, and firſt wickedneſſe of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> the firſt king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two other, by the misbeleeuers of the ſame people. Oh, that the leprous among the papiſts,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12130:37"/>who in outwarde appearance haue faire fleſh, but are all rotten and putrified within, who in exterieur deuotion, and faigned ſimplicity, in habits, in Ceremonies, and publicke actions, ſeeme eſpeciall men, and to exceed all other, &amp; yet vnderneath, are nothing but vlcered with enuy, pride, and gluttony, with all other kindes of voluptuouſneſſe: who are a people that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and thruſt out vice, to the eies of the world, and yet retaine and call it in againe at a backe doore: Oh, that they would ſeeke their owne cure, in the learned writings of <hi>Our King Iames</hi> or <hi>Iacobus,</hi> By the Lambe with ſeauen hornes, and ſeauen eyes, by the ſeauen Spirits of God, and the ſeuenth aſperſion or ſprinckling of the Leuiticall bloud.</p>
            <p>And comming to Diuination, by the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers appropriated to their Carracters, excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated firſt of all by <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> the Traditions whereof are no other thing, but a very He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew <hi>Cabala,</hi> grounded vppon this place in the Booke of <hi>wiſedome:</hi> God hath made al things in number, waight, and meaſure: wee ſhall there find, that this onely name ΙΑΚΩΒΟΣ in Greeke, ſurmounteth double almoſt the name and the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12130:38"/>Number of the Beaſt, in all Languages and tongues, which is not without ſome ſpecial mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, neither without the prouidence of God: whereunto neither <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> nor <hi>Ptolome</hi> do any way contradict, but rather they auouch, that Letters do containe in them (miſtically) certain numbers, and that in the proper names of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſome ſecret matter is contained of their Fortunes and Deſtinies. As we may ſee by theſe verſes, traduced and drawne out of that olde Grammarian <hi>Terentianus,</hi> which ſheweth vnto vs both the vſe and the practiſe thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <l>One tels vs, that the verse names,</l>
               <l>in Letters do containe</l>
               <l>The Fortunes of the greatest men,</l>
               <l>and those of lower straine.</l>
               <l>If both do venter to oppose</l>
               <l>and tempt the God of Warre:</l>
               <l>To vse his Armes; the Lot to each;</l>
               <l>will differ very farre.</l>
               <l>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictorie will fall vnto</l>
               <l>the greater numbers name,</l>
               <l>The lesser thereby gaineth harme,</l>
               <l>perhaps, mischance and shame.</l>
               <l>For so it was great Hectors hap,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Patrocles</hi> to confound:</l>
               <l>And then <hi>Achilles</hi> (by wanes chance)</l>
               <l>laid <hi>Hector</hi> on the ground.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In like manner, our Royall Name, which notes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12130:38"/>and markes the thouſand years and more, that the raigne of Antichriſt hath continued power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and with authority; that his blaſphemies againſt God, his cruelty againſt his Saints, his fowling with his feet the ſpiritual <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the propheſie of the witneſſes of God, to annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the true and inuiſible Church, becauſe they were laide as deade and dumbe, in the viſible, exteriour and pretended Church, the flight of the Spouſe of Chriſt into the wilderneſſe, and that ſhe became inuiſible: In all theſe doe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount (at this inſtant) the name of the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>For, be it that he call himſelfe <hi>Apphipior</hi> in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> or ΛΑΤΕΙΝΟΣ in <hi>Greek</hi> (to omit <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Die Lux,</hi> which are neyther names of men, nor of the Latine Empire: no more then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are not of the firſt beſt) or <hi>Papa</hi> in <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. Iacob</hi> ſhall triumph daily, and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly, on the number which is found in <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Quintus, Vice-Deo</hi> (a <hi>Vize-God.</hi>) <hi>Heer is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom He that hath vnderſtanding, let him count the number of the Beaſt:</hi> for it is the number of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and his number is ſix hundred ſixty ſix, &amp; that of ΙΑΚΩΒΟΣ of a King, which containeth ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12130:39"/>hundred and three.</p>
            <p>That which wanteth of forty two months, of a thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall, of three great dayes and an halfe; of a time, of times, and of halfe a time, mentioned in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and in the <hi>Apocalipſe:</hi> al do ſignify the ſame tearme or ſpace of time, and each, one thouſand, two hundred and ſixty <hi>Iulian</hi> years, which is ſince the diminiſhing and fall of the kingdome of Antechriſt, and which ſhall bee wholly ouerthrowne by <hi>Our Prince,</hi> accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in his Numbers.</p>
            <p>As the hundred ſeauenth King of Scotland, he hath contributed more alone by himſelf, to build the Temple of God, and to reforme the ſeruice therein, then all the Kinges together haue done, or all the people of <hi>Aſia,</hi> to raiſe that proud Temble of <hi>Dyna</hi> (named by the Greeks <hi>Agrotarius,</hi> or <hi>Elaphobolos</hi>) which was a wonder of the world, and the Ornament of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his number hath this reſpect, that it is compoſed of two perfect numbers. Of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, which is tenne times tenne, wherein God is maruailouſly pleaſed. For <hi>Iacob</hi> bought an hundered Lambes for an heritage which he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12130:39"/>had in <hi>Syria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Children of Iſraell gaue an hundered Tallents, where-with was made three Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bordes, for the Veſſelles which were placed neere vnto the Tabernacle The <hi>Romains</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues were not ignorant of the power and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this number, hauing builded the Temple of <hi>Mars</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> with an hundred Collomnes, &amp; their Senate conſiſted of an hundred Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors. And <hi>Iulian</hi> in his Epiſtle vnto <hi>Serapion,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Creet</hi> had an hundred Towns or Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Thebes</hi> an hundred gates, ſome Altars an hundered feete, ſome Sacrifices an hundered beaſts, and continually an hundered Souldiers to ſeuerall Centurions.</p>
            <p>But in what part of the world is to be found, ſo long a ſucceſsion of Kinges in the right line, without interruption or breach? Turne ouer all the Worlde, ſearch into all families, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Monarchies, the Empires and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, count all their Kings one by one, their Emperors, their Monarkes, and you ſhal neuer finde ſo great a number, neither any Raigne: which hath endured for the ſpace of 1908.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12130:40"/>without euer being ſubiugated, like vnto ours, or that goeth before vs in the ſuſception of Chriſtianity, and profeſsion of the Catholique Faith.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Chriſti tranſactis tribus annis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ducentis</l>
               <l>Scotia Catholicam coepit inire fidem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Since <hi>Donaldus,</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King, he is the 79. who being multiplyed one by another in their times, it produceth prognoſtically the moſt dangerous Climacteriall age of Poperie, or the Papacy: as their ſimple tranſpoſition marketh the yeare of the Reuelation Written by Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> and the laſt apart by it ſelfe, did facilitate the way for him to his ſecond Crown, and to vs the ſence of this Arithmeticall predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by the effect.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Galla feret natum, cui tota Britannia laeta</l>
               <l>Subijciet collum refluo circumſona Ponto</l>
               <l>Nec proprior quam nonus erit de ſanguine Bruti.</l>
            </q>
            <p>His perfection likewiſe is ſeen in this, that he hath the name of <hi>Iames</hi> the ſixt of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Sixe being the ſigne of accompliſhment, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerueth it to be that onely amongſt numbers ſimple, which reſolueth all the parts, and maketh them equal, to wit; of one, of two,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12130:40"/>and of three. This is a number very pleaſing &amp; acceptable to God, and which himſelf hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the moſt part of his maruellous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Six dayes he laboured and wrought in the perfection of the world: Sixe dayes hee rained <hi>Manna</hi> in the wilderneſſe, and diſtributed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men the bread of Angels. Sixe dayes <hi>Moſes</hi> conferred with him, about the eternall decrees of his will, and on the Articles of Religion: he willed that the Wals of <hi>Iericho</hi> ſhould be ſixe times circuted about, before they were to bee tumbled to the ground. Six dayes he kept ſhut the gates of his Temple, which looked towards the Eaſt, and commaunded that ſixe Lambes ſhould bee offered to him, on each day of the Sabaoth in ſacrifice: wee may alſo ſay, that hee hath recommended this number in Nature, as it being his will, that (among floures) the Lilly ſhould haue ſix leaues: Among ſtones, the <hi>Iris</hi> ſhould haue ſix Corners: and that the Lyon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in her firſt whelping, ſhold haue ſix yong ones, and that ſo decaying continually vnto one, ſhe ſhould terminate her brood in an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is the bottome, the beginning, and the onely ſourſe of all other numbers.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12130:41"/>
            <p>Jn the ſame ſort is hee called and choſen of God (without any doubt) the ſixt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be the firſt, not onely of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> but alſo euerie where. Becauſe in this <hi>Vnitie,</hi> the <hi>Veritie</hi> is founde, who is but <hi>Onely One,</hi> and as <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus</hi> ſaith, <hi>The beginning and the roote of All.</hi> He is the firſt alſo of <hi>Tenne Kings Chriſtians, that should hate the whore, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her become naked and deſolate, should eate hir flesh, and burne her with fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So may we alſo ſay, that hee hath chaunged his Name (like vnto <hi>Iacob</hi>) to reſemble him in all thinges. Of the ſixt, hee is come to bee the firſt, and of King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; of <hi>England,</hi> he is now the King of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Iam cuncti Gens vna ſumus</l>
               <l>Et Simus in aeuum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And for the fulfilling or accompliſhment of this old vaticination.</p>
            <q>Imperium, Faſces, C. Faſtus Sceptra, Triumphus Quae fuerant: penitus C. veniente cadent.</q>
            <p>He ought of right, as wel as by his Baptiſme,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12130:41"/>to be called <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, a more iuſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle then that of <hi>Antiochus, Quintus Fabius, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey, Methridates,</hi> and the reſt: or they that are yet called the Great <hi>Chams</hi> of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> or the dreaded <hi>Othomans.</hi> For if <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this Name onely, for hauing ſuccoured the Church; and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> onely for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting the Empire from ſo many imminent daungers: what Name can be found conuena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto his Deuotion and deſſeign, to deliuer all Chriſtendome from the Tyranny of Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? Whome may a man tearme to bee more Great, then he which is the <hi>Non pareil,</hi> of all that are, or may bee in this preſent Age?</p>
            <p>Hee is Great, according to the World, and in all that which the worlde eſteemeth to bee great, as the Scripture ſayeth, <hi>According to the Name Greatneſse on the earth.</hi> Great in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Prouinces; Great in Landes and Seigneuries, Great in Authoritie and power, Great in Armes and Treaſures, Great in Nobilitie and Lineage, Great in Age and youth. And euery way ſo Great in all theſe,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12130:42"/>as being not to be equalled by any, hee is <hi>The Great of Greats, the Chiefeſt and the moſt Great of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which is much morethen all theſe, and whereunto the world cannot attaine; hee is <hi>Great</hi> according to God; great in Faith and Religion, Great in Vertue and Faithfulneſſe, Great in Iuſtice and Piety, Great in kindneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anſutude, Great in Goodneſſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, Great in wiſedome and experience, Great in name, &amp; more Great in effects. Brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is the liuely Image of Great <hi>Hercules,</hi> who neuer did or thought on any thing, but it was Great, and greatly profitable. All his actions, al his wordes and cogitations, are nothing but Great.</p>
            <p>It is a thing moſt certaine, that God doeth euermore raiſe Great perſonages, whom hee indueth with excellent and Heroical vertues, to finiſh fortunately whatſoeuer hee committeth into their hands. The which is alſo teſtified by a moſt eſpeciall prouidence of God, euen in his Sur-name of <hi>(Steuart,)</hi> thereby being oppoſed gainſt Antechriſt, as the South-winde againſt the North-wind, that is to ſay; as Grace againſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12130:42"/>ſinne, and as the bleſſed Spirit againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, who is the true North-wind, from whence all euill commeth vpon all the inhabitantes of the earth. And this is conformable to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where ſpeaking of them that are <hi>Faithfull Miniſters,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Good Stewards</hi> in our Language, and whoſe workes God hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in verity, and made a perpetual league or couenant with them: It is ſaide, that <hi>Their ſeede shall be knowne among the Gentiles, &amp; their encreaſe shal be in the midſt of the people.</hi> As it was ſeene in the <hi>Macchabees,</hi> who by beeing of the ſeede of them, by whome ſaluation came to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, this bleſsing was beſtowed vpon them.</p>
            <p>Now, this houſe of <hi>Steuart</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> is as a Phoenix among the Nobility, the Lords ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are as <hi>Nectors</hi> among men, for the length of time that their race hath liued. For ſince the yeare of Grace, 1057. from the raigne of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colme,</hi> euen to this preſent, it hath flouriſhed ful of proſperity and honour. All the Kings iſſued of that line, haue taken hands with him, and (as by infuſion) tranſmitted their rare and excellent qualities, ſtill from one to another, neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating: for euermore Royall Eagles doo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12130:43"/>produce Imperial Eagles, Eagles that haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually made War with Dragons, with Foxes, and (aboue all) with Serpents.</p>
            <p>As is now to be ſeene in our <hi>Great King,</hi> who hath producted the moſt Noble Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> (the ninth in Sur-name among Kinges in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as of Name in <hi>England</hi>) for the greater height of his good fortune.</p>
            <p>This young Prince is a warrior alreadie, both in geſture and countenance, ſo that in looking on him, he ſeemeth vnto vs, that in him we do yet ſee <hi>Aiax</hi> before <hi>Troy,</hi> crowding among the armed Troops, calling vnto them, that he may ioyne body to body with <hi>Hector,</hi> who ſtandes trembling with chill-cold feare, to ſee him ſeek to determine the difference in the incloſed Field or Liſts. Hee can neuer permit, that anie other ſhould ſtep before him in an occaſion ſo remarkable. Honour was all his nouriture, and Greatneſſe his paſtime (as it was ſaide of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander) and Triumph the ordinary end of al his Actions. What though his deſires bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached by a much ſtronger deſire, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoire retarded by a Naturall dutie, and by an obedience, which in this occaſion only is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12130:43"/>and contrary to his owne affection? Yet let it not be immagined, that the execution of great deſſeignes, are vtterly loſt by deferrence and delay. Deferred, not in regarde of weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or impuiſſance, but referred to fit ſeaſon, to do nothing againſt the order of Nature, or contrarie to the will of his father: who woulde alwayes haue his Sonne for Obiect, and ſubiect of contentment by his preſence. Contrarie to the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> who coulde not, nor can endure the youngneſſe of their Children, their very ſhadow gaines them ſo many other ſuſpicious ſhaddowes, and their preſence excludeth them from all kinds of pleaſures.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie hath alſo another Sonne, Duke Charles, who ſhineth in the two Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> like the other twinne-Starre, and who promiſeth vs, that as the Sun is at the very higheſt in <hi>Gemini:</hi> euen ſo, God in the ſame maner, will very quickly raiſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> in the <hi>Apogaeum</hi> of his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And that hee will make the ſucceſsion of the houſe of <hi>Steuart,</hi> not onely equally vnto the worlds continuance, but the world it ſelf equal
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12130:44"/>to his ſucceſsion, and to the ſacred ſtirpe of his Maieſty. This is it, wherunto the full end of his greatneſſe is aſsigned, and where he hath laide the baſes of his very greateſt Trophees: This is the point where his Angle endeth, this is the extreamity of his line, and this is the center of his circumference.</p>
            <p>Wherein we diſcern (at laſt ſight) the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the houſe of <hi>Cyrus</hi> (which was of ſmall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance, becauſe they did not acknowledge God who elected them) to that of <hi>Our King,</hi> whom he multiplieth &amp; encreaſeth euery day, awaiting vntill God ſhall come from the ſouth, to chaſe away that rude Oxe, and diſſolue the captiuity of the Waters which are frozen, to make them run in Torrents, and like Riuers in the South. That is to ſay, the extermination of Antichriſts race, by that of <hi>Steuart,</hi> to deliuer thoſe poore ſoules, which vnder the coldneſſe of this barbarous impiety are ſo miſerably cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiued, by the heate of the South, which is the Grace of the Holy ghoſt, and Faith and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian piety. That the garden of the Spouſe may be ſo breathed by this wind, as the odorifferous iuices thereof may diſtill on all ſides, by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12130:44"/>of holineſſe and deuotion in all the waies vpon earth, and cauſing that they which are at the South (as it is written in <hi>Abdias</hi>) that is to ſay, the true Chriſtians which are in the South, ſhall poſſeſſe the Mount of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and make themſelues Maiſters of that Eſtate: Euen ſo may we hope one day to ſee, that vnder the name and family of <hi>Steuart,</hi> all Chriſtendome ſhall flouriſh in an abſolute Monarchy.</p>
            <p>For the Maiſter, who hath placed him ouer his houſholde, to giue them all thinges in due time, hath found him a faithfull and wiſe <hi>Spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Steward,</hi> or a good <hi>Oeconomicus</hi> in his dealing. Wherefore he hath ſaid vnto vs, that (in very deed) he will commit all his goodes to him. And the Lord who hath giuen him thoſe fiue tallents in keeping, when he taketh his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of him, will find that he hath made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of them, that he hath gained fiue more by &amp; aboue them. Wherefore he will ſay vnto him; <hi>It is well done good ſeruant, thou haſt bin faithful in a few ſmall things, I will ſet and conſtitute thee ouer much more, enter into the ioy of thy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the reſt, <hi>Romaine</hi> antiquity hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that in the family of the <hi>Fabij</hi> there were
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12130:45"/>three Princes of the Senate; In that of the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij,</hi> three Orators: In ſome ſo many Cenſors, In others, as many Dictators. But in the family of the <hi>Steuarts,</hi> there are not three or foure to be noted, but many great Lords and Princes, who haue all made apparance of the greatnes of their valour throughout the world, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly they that are of the braunch of Noble <hi>Lennox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their piety appeared with Saint <hi>Lewes:</hi> their courage againſt your enemies <hi>(O French-men)</hi> and their fidelity at al times towards the Realm of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> our Chronicles doe report them. Alſo the memory of thoſe voyages in the Eaſt, doe witneſſe them, and your Hiſtories them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are ful of their praiſes: which whoſoeuer ſhall read, wil find them as ſo many ſharp ſpurs inciting to vertue. Such as haue read the manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts of that race, or ſeen <hi>The Galleries of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerye</hi> in <hi>Soulongne,</hi> wil confeſſe, that they neuer read either among the Greekes or Latines, any thing comming neere to their naturall genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. From this vertue came it, to aduance <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Berault Steuart,</hi> Lorde of <hi>Aubigny,</hi> and of <hi>Croitet,</hi> Knight of the Order, Captayne of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12130:45"/>Guard to his <hi>Ma-body,</hi> Great Conſtable of <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily</hi> and of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and his Highneſſe Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall in the kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi> And hence, an infinite number of other, al Captains of Guard to the Body, of the Chamber, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, Marſhals, or Conſtables of France. And hence alſo <hi>Meſsire Bernard Steuart,</hi> Marſhall of <hi>France,</hi> that gaue ſo much exerciſe vnto the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift: who vanquiſhed, and tooke Priſoner in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> that great Romaine Captaine <hi>Proſper Colonnus,</hi> in the yeare 1515. according to the Relation of our French Authors. And whence at this inſtant is ſprung,</p>
            <q>Dux inter primos praeſtanti corpore LENOX.</q>
            <p>who for his excellent and ſinguler partes, hath not forſaken vs, althogh he be called into <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> to bee the Honour of Honors to the French. Let the <hi>Parthians</hi> vaunt them of their <hi>Arſaces,</hi> the Greeks of their <hi>Egides,</hi> and the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muines</hi> of their <hi>Emilij, Fabij, Curij,</hi> and <hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li: Great Brittaine,</hi> makes vaunt of her <hi>Steuarts,</hi> and of nothing more then of her <hi>Steuarts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Nec Phoebo gratior vlla eſt</l>
               <l>Principis haec quam quae praefixit pagina nomen.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:12130:46"/>
            <p>Prince moſt generous and Magnanimious, happy <hi>Henry,</hi> the delight of <hi>Heauen,</hi> the loue of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Titus</hi> of humaine kinde, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer feare that the victories of MY KING will leaue you nothing to conquer. Enter not into that ambitious ielouſy with <hi>Alexander,</hi> who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fortunat progreſſe of his Fathers affairs, &amp; how victoriouſly he went on, ioyning Citty to Citty, and Prouince to Prouince: Surely (quoth he to his ſouldiers) my Father will win all, and leaue nothing famous or Magnificent for me to conquer with you. You muſt triumph with him, as did the Sonnes of <hi>Emilius,</hi> and of <hi>Commodus,</hi> with their Fathers, and the children of <hi>Marcus Caeſar,</hi> with <hi>Mark Anthony.</hi> In fights, the diſpoſition and order muſt be committed to his iudgement, and his iudgement muſt bee referred to the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ſword, againſt all Refractaties. Yours ſhall bee the arme and ſtrength, but his the head and Counſel; Yours the paine and endeuour, his the effect; Yours the Action, but he the Agent: You for him, &amp; he for you, and you and hee ioyntly together, ſhall win an immortall glory; to the end, that al the world may ſee you in effect after the ſame
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12130:46"/>manner, as one figured Caeſar, aloft, depoſing or treading a Globe vnder him, holding a book in one hand, and a ſword in the other: ſo that it may be ſaide of you, <hi>That for the one &amp; other you are a</hi> Caeſar.</p>
            <p>And you Prince and Duke, Duke &amp; Prince, <hi>Charles,</hi> Beloued of all, who may holde it as much honour to be called Sonne to the King of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Scicily,</hi> Brother of Saint <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes,</hi> to name himſelfe Son to the K. of <hi>France:</hi> or <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and of <hi>Valencia,</hi> in the ſame manner. Remember that you are the Sonne of a King, as <hi>Menedemus</hi> ſaide in the eare of young <hi>Antigonus;</hi> You, the excellencie of my <hi>Hope,</hi> and the <hi>Sacred Anker</hi> of him who ſeeketh no other happineſſe in this world, then in your ſeruice, neither any honour, then what may be pleaſing vnto you. Methinkes I ſee a Sword in your hand, and you vpon the walles of <hi>Nicomedia, Nicea, Antioche,</hi> and <hi>Tripoli,</hi> ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at the faireſt through all perilles, euen in the leſſer Aſia, &amp; take perforce <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> again by aſſault, after the ſiedge of fiue and thirtie dayes. Go generous Race, go gather Laurels
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12130:47"/>in the fieldes of <hi>Armenia,</hi> enfrachiſe the <hi>Palus Maeotides,</hi> enter into <hi>Lycaonia, Bricea, Traba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonde,</hi> chaſe the <hi>Turbants</hi> from thoſe Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and making a new world, ſur-name thoſe Prouinces after your Name.</p>
            <p>Who ſteppes vp, to driue the <hi>Lydian</hi> out of his houſe, and leaue nothing but the <hi>Tarteſian</hi> Cat? Oh, that I might ſee MY KING glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vniuerſally, and Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> made Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in the loue of Chriſtendome, and to the aſtoniſhment of the Infidels! Oh, that with one common hand wee might Warre on the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometane,</hi> and that his Trophees might no more be ſhamefull Markes of our generall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity! Let vs be the firſt vpon their ſquadrons, and (all armed) march for the conqueſt of the Holy-Land, ſo much honored by God, by the beginning of his Church. Let vs croſſe the ſeas, and as they, who (to animate others) cryed in the Shippe, <hi>Itorus, Itorus,</hi> the Maiſter, ſay; Behold heere is the Maſter. Let vs be the firſt to aduance our Standards, vpon the Ramparts of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> daunting all them that ſhall ſeek to tardie our deſſeignes, and let vs free the way to the whole Army, to the end, that</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:12130:47"/>
            <q>
               <l>In raigne ſo great of ſuch a great raigne raigning,</l>
               <l>By force of Armes, the greateſt gates of Braſſe</l>
               <l>Were made to open: the King and Duke ſo ioyning</l>
               <l>Beat downe, ſunke Shippes, a fairer day neere was.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And that inſteade of a Tyrant Fratricide, My Lord and Maiſter might be honoured, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and obeyed, as the lawfull Prince, and true nouriſher of his ſubiects.</p>
            <p>You alſo Duke and Prince, a Peere ſans Peer, in all Great Brittaine; You the <hi>Iolaus</hi> of our <hi>Hercules,</hi> the <hi>Claterus</hi> and the <hi>Hepheſtion</hi> of <hi>Our</hi> ALEXANDER; You my <hi>Omphis,</hi> my <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor,</hi> according as <hi>Xenocrates</hi> called his <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter:</hi> Remember that you are a Branch of this great Tree. Looke in the olde Tables of your Predeceſſors, and their Lawrels all duſtie, but with the duſt of Honor. You wiſe and prudent <hi>Lodowicke,</hi> honoured ſo many times with roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all honors of <hi>Lenox, Grace</hi> of <hi>Graces,</hi> that haue left <hi>France</hi> (your Natiue country) to be alwaies by and at the right hand of <hi>Our King,</hi> as not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to looſe the ſight of him; neither be further off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Maieſty, then the Sun fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick line. You that giue ſo many wholſom coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſels for the preſeruation of his eſtate &amp; perſon:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12130:48"/>giue likewiſe your Vowes and Prayers to that <hi>Iupiter Hypſiſtius,</hi> which is the moſt high God, that Hereſie may for euer be ſtifled, and by the ſame Diuinity of Our King, which is his chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt practiſe, his owne aduiſe, in aſſaying to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the little wandering flocke to the folde of the Church, by a National counſel, or one Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenical or Vniuerſall, it cannot but bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. This is the onely remedy for theſe euilles (as his Maieſty very well acknowledgeth) and the beſt meanes to conuert the moſt Learned, and leſſer oppinitiue. This is the voyce, wiſh and deſire, yea, euen the very finall cutting off, of all our pretended Romaine Catholiques.</p>
            <p>To take excuſe from the one ſide, and giue pretext to the other, as it behooueth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them <hi>Viua voce</hi> (as they haue been often enough by learned writings, as well of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, as by others) before they bee conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. That we might ſee (with patience) their Reaſons layde on the boord, and our Combate with them, to be in mildnes and modeſty: This is the deſſeigne of my diſcourſe, and the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of my <hi>Paraeneſis,</hi> or accompliſhment of my wiſh. Oh, that you might ſee theſe temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12130:48"/>ſpirites, which hurle duſt in the eyes of trueth, in thinking to dazell ours, ſhould yeild vp their Weapons into the hands of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, to offer them at his ſeruice, and take the Oath of his faithfull obedience. You ſhoulde ſee them ſuddainly ſurprized, like the compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Cilones</hi> conſpiracy, at the Temple of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua,</hi> and all run in zeale of affection, to the Palmes, Laurels and Crownes, which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty hath propoſed as their recompence, in ſuch an happy and profitable conuerſion.</p>
            <p>All ſuch as are capable of the aduancement of ſuch a fruitfull deſſeigne, ought to beſtowe their watchfull paines and Trauaile, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and the ſafety of the King, for the conuerſion or confuſion of all our papiſts, and for the quiet of our Countrey, if not of all the whole world.</p>
            <p>Nor do I thinke heerein, that any one ought to be ſo arrogant or ouer-weening as he ſhold ſeeke to giue a Leſſon of wiſedom to <hi>My Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned King,</hi> or ſhould teach his experience, or cleare his knowledge, or be a guide to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion for following time: Neither thinke I, that there is any one ſo bold-faced or preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12130:49"/>as to cenſure his proceedings paſt, or to come. In either of theſe arrogancies, we ſhould behold but a Souldiour-like <hi>Phormio;</hi> an Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>earde <hi>Mydas,</hi> a Croote-noſed <hi>Corebus,</hi> a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Hiſſer,</hi> a prating <hi>Xenophanes,</hi> and one alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether like to <hi>Mineruaes</hi> Hog, or <hi>Apollos Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyas:</hi> &amp; I ſhould repute ſuch a <hi>Hermes</hi> without ſhame, worthy the paines and puniſhment of <hi>Hermea,</hi> his Maieſty being more able then any other, to giue forme to euery action, and hath neuer forced (by wheele or fire) violently their conſciences. But it is to this end, that you, who do face to face contemplate the diuinity of <hi>My King,</hi> might be the Mediator of ſuch a holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, &amp; that boldly, and with open mouth you would tell him, that the whole world ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth the accompliſhment of his aduiſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by himſelfe, or neuer.</p>
            <p>Becauſe that God by his Grace, hath ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with a ſinguler &amp; ſupereminent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a King, not ſo much in fauour of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors (as he did to the houſe of <hi>Laban,</hi> for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> of <hi>Putipher</hi> the <hi>Egiptian,</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and to <hi>Salomon,</hi> for loue to his Father <hi>Dauid</hi>) as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his owne propper merrites, in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12130:49"/>as he ſaide to <hi>Abraham:</hi> He foreſaw his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and his dilligence, in wel inſtructing his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and his poſterity after him, and that hee ſhould acknowledge to holde his Crowne of him, and not of any other.</p>
            <p>Wherein we may ſee, that he is King, not by the neighing of a horſe, like to <hi>Darius,</hi> nor by the flight of an Eagle, like to <hi>Aegon</hi> in the Citty of <hi>Argos,</hi> nor by vncertaine report, as to <hi>Alyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Paphos,</hi> nor by the Lance, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was made Emperonr, nor by the ſword, as <hi>Seruius,</hi> nor by tyrany, as <hi>Nero,</hi> nor by adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>Caius Luciius Caeſars:</hi> But by extraction, not by election, which hee would neuer haue beene, how euer <hi>Tortus</hi> (to his Graund tort) ſpeakes it. But by the Grace of God, as his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie doth confeſſe it, by inheritance and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion, like <hi>Octauian,</hi> bearing the Crowne one way by his byrth, as his Thiſtle declareth, and the other by patience, as did <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> being both by right of bloud and merite, the chiefeſt Prince.</p>
            <p>It is an high gift of God, to com into the world in ſuch a ranke and degree, as to beare away a Crown by being borne to it: but to deſerue it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12130:50"/>he touch it, and thereby to fill the whole world with his name, that makes him double woorthy thereof, and he rather honoureth the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, then he receiueth any honour thereby.</p>
            <p>But it ſeemes, that they would make him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Lande (all ſhining in felicity) by a falſe doore: by feare, by hope, &amp;c. which is not onely to make a commerce of Kingdomes, and to Traffique with Scepters: but likewiſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to open ſale, euen the heauens and ſoules of men.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Vaenalia Romae</l>
               <l>Templa, Sacerdotes, Altaria, Sacra, Coronae,</l>
               <l>Ignes, Thura, Preces, Coelum eſt vaenale, Deuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And what is it? That the King of Scottes had giuen ſome hope of his Apoſtaſie from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to be King of <hi>England.</hi> Can any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it? This came from ſo many Monſters, as diſloyalty &amp; perfidie of thoſe Miniſters would builde in the fantaſtical braines of the Pope and his Cardinals. Rather the ſun retrograde in the South, ſhall returne and waſh his faire locks in the Orientall billows, and the earth once more drowned with another deluge, ſhal accuſe <hi>Iris</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:12130:50"/>of lying; then <hi>My King</hi> ſhoulde, or euer did think to promiſe ſuch a wickedneſſe: That the faith, of the <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> would ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it ſelfe, and cauſe him to yeilde homage to one without faith, and makes publick profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of violating all Faith: That the promiſe of a Prince (the very abſtract of all vertuous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) ſhould be ſubiected to the wicked paſsions or pretences of any whatſoeuer? That a puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Monarchy, which could euen then extend her right hand, for the terrour of his enemyes, and ruine of them as duſt reſiſt againſt his iuſt right, would render vp her <hi>Lord, King,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> by perfidie or ſubtilty, to eſtabliſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the Fox, and forſake the ſigne of <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, no, this might eaſily haue beene done with an <hi>Athenian</hi> or <hi>Melian Diagoras,</hi> or a <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renian Theodorus,</hi> and many other Empirickes of State, who had much rather take part with earth then heauen, and who for a meſſe of Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Pottage, would turne their backes on God. But not with ſuch a Prince as he, who from his Cradle, hath beene nurſed with the bloud and ſucke of Lyons; I meane in his Religion, truely a Chriſtian, and which hath taught him, that it is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12130:51"/>the Faith which makes him acceptable in the ſight of that great King of Kinges, and which alſo muſt one day make him Triumph, with a Crowne of infinite glory, far beyond the ioyes of faigned <hi>Eliſium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was for the firſt King of <hi>Athens Cecrops,</hi> to be double, as alſo the Courtier of <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who was named <hi>Hecateros,</hi> to bee both the one and other, and it fitteth well the Ieſuites, to equiuocate: but not a man of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſuch as <hi>My King</hi> is, who carrieth his hart vpon his tongue, and ſpeakes from the bottom of his ſtomacke, as <hi>Homer</hi> makes his <hi>Vliſſes</hi> to ſpeake, immooueable, and euermore in full waight, vpon his duty both towardes God and men, keeping his faith and promiſes to enemies themſelues, <hi>Verus Iſraelita in quo dolus non eſt:</hi> knowing verie well, that God loues no craft, cunning and diſſembling, and affected the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke <hi>Iacob</hi> ſo much, becauſe he was without all fictions</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ir bonus &amp; ſapiens, lingua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; pectore verus,</l>
               <l>Iuſtitiae cultor rigidi ſeruator honeſti.</l>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <l>A man both good and wiſe,</l>
               <l>in tongue and minde full true:</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:12130:51"/>
               <l>Adoring Iuſtice, coole and calme,</l>
               <l>and naught but honeſt knew.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, to deale and cope with the enuious and perfidious, malignity of theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators, euen at their owne weapons, let vs admit, that the king had treated of his Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, before an examining bench at Rome, that hee promiſed to make himſelf a Papiſt in intention, or wholly at a free leape, without ſhame, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out piety, &amp; Chriſtian feare of that great dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, that he would haue forſaken the loue of God, the care of his own ſaluation, and of all eternity. Shall wee not heere conſider, that the world, that te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall interſes may be made with them (for the matter of Religion) as a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of Marchandize? And when all this had bin done, where are then his ſo much vantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able profits? Jt ſhould haue bin very ſmall, to make the greatnes of his Throne, the foot pace of the Pope, and miſerable were his condition, if in ſted of hauing heauen for his Aſpect, the earth for foundation, and the ſea for limit, hee ſhould conſent that his ſcepter &amp; Crown muſt be ſubiected, to the perturbations &amp; appetites of a Prieſt. This were, to eſtabliſh another Kingdome in his Kingdome, to admitte an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12130:52"/>King aboue him, which would be as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious, &amp; occaſion as much hurt, as two Suns ſhining at once in heauen, which would ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all. The plurallity of Caeſars (ſayeth an ancient Writer) is dangerous, and the Poet,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—All greatneſſe Royall,</l>
               <l>By no meanes can endure to haue an equall.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now I am of the minde, that his Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, in attributing to himſelfe this qualitie, or this Title of King, doeth vnderſtand it alſo in the ſame manner as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpake of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Greatneſſe and Authority. It is I (ſaith he, vnder the perſon of a potent Emperour) who haue beene ſo acceptable to the Gods, as they haue choſen me for their Lieutenant on earth. It is I that ſecond them, It is by my mouth, that they pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their determinations immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and the good or euil fortunes of men.</p>
            <p>For, beſide the authorities and prerogatiues in common, which his maieſty hath with other Kinges, that they are rich in quantity, hauing this quality, as being happy in hauing this qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as being happy in hauing this contentment, to ſay; <hi>I will,</hi> and it is doone; <hi>I deſire,</hi> and the deſire is accompliſhed. That the very winke of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12130:52"/>the eye makes them to be vnderſtood, the leaſt changing of their lookes, procureth execution of their will, and that they can wiſh nothing more in earth, becauſe he that is a King, is All, according to the aunſwere of King <hi>Porus:</hi> yet ouer and aboue theſe perticuler aduantages which GOD hath giuen him, as making the Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> by the right of their eldeſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; this word KING, doth ſhew vs his faith pure and cleane towards God, by his Charitie &amp; fatherly loue vnto his Subiects, and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence in the affaires of his Crowne. For, in our French Language, it conſiſteth of 3. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>ROI,</hi> and alſo in Latine REX, as the primordials and Radicall Letters of the <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> and of one Syllable, which ſimbolizeth (in ſome ſort) with the moſt holy and Sacred <hi>Ternarie</hi> or Trinity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the Letter <hi>R.</hi> (according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations which concern <hi>Socrates</hi> in the <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylis</hi> of <hi>Plato</hi>) it ſignifieth vnto vs, his continuall action and exerciſe of duty, for the acquitting of his charge, as the toong remoueth ſtrongly &amp; without any ſtay, in the pronouncing it. <hi>O,</hi> denoteth the roundnes which he equally vſeth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12130:53"/>towards euery one, which, as it is round, equal &amp; euen, without any points, or corners to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it out abroad: ſo it ſheweth, that <hi>Our King</hi> is perfectly round, ſeeing that his words and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do concord, and that both to one &amp; other he goes in full rotundity, plainneſſe and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſpeaking euermore with a round mouth. As J, doth alſo repreſent his lenity and mildneſſe, by a facile and very gracious prolation.</p>
            <p>And according to the Traditions of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſts,</hi> the Letter RESH doth infer, that hee is King by ſucceſsion, and inſtructeth vs, that Hereditary kingdomes are much better inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then thoſe which bee elected: where the combuſtions of ſuites and partialities, do often times cauſe them to turne their backes on their enemies, with extreame affliction, and ruine of the people. <hi>(O)</hi> is as the eie, which he lendeth to al, and ouer all, in imitation whereof, the <hi>Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> in their Hierogliphicks, did repreſent roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty by an Eye, placed vppon the top of a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>(I)</hi> wherof al the Hebrew Letters are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and which by the ſame means conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the number of ten, the perfection, reſting place, and accompliſhment of all other num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12130:53"/>doth ſignifie thereby, that all the parts and members of his kingdome, do depend intirely vpon him, wherefore, al ought to bee referred to his ſafety and preſeruation.</p>
            <p>Thus paſsing theſe myſtical Interpretations, and ſignifications of theſe three Letters, to that which might reſult fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their diuers Anagrams, Metatheſis, and Renuerſements, according to the <hi>Tmurah</hi> and <hi>Siruphs</hi> of the <hi>Haebrewes,</hi> Our King (as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaieth in the life of <hi>Moyfes</hi>) is a Soule-like Lawe, and his <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>Our Iuſt-King,</hi> they are ſo bound by the girdle of the Graces, and ioyned together by Iuſtice.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Iuſtitiae cupidus recto non deuius vnquam.</q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">Deſire of Iuſtice neuer ſwerues from right.</q>
            <p>For although <hi>Cato</hi> was woont to ſay, that a King was a rauenous Beaſt; that hee liued not but by his prey, and on Veniſon or wilde food: yet can not it ſo be ſaid of <hi>Our King,</hi> ſeeing hee contents himſelfe with a ſmall circumference, not inſulting vpon his Neighbors or Strangers. Neuer did any man hear in him, that ouerbold wiſh of the Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> (by the report of <hi>Phillip de Commines</hi>) to bee a God, <hi>And that his Sonne might be King of France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:12130:54"/>
            <p>His deſire, and the chiefeſt degree of his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, is to be called King of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> which is the kingdom of the Church of God, his part and portion which he hath choſen in earth, &amp; the kingdome which ſucceedeth to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Iuda.</hi> This is the Chriſtian kingdom, wherein euen to the very leaſt or vulgar, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (elſe-where) bee found a people more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout and Religious: Piety and Religion are there ſo zealouſly, and ſo often exerciſed. In breefe, <hi>It is the Land of Promiſe,</hi> which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to himſelfe in Chriſtendome, where he hath ſo long time kept the Booke open, and the Reuelation of his Prophetick and Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Myſteries. God himſelfe Husbanded the Garden of that Country, and tooke thee euen meaſures thereof, hauing enguirt it with the great Ocean. As concerning the forme of the Iſland (according to the opinion and deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Caeſar</hi>) it is triangulare, whereof one way is oppoſit and faceth <hi>France,</hi> and containeth on that ſide, about ſixe ſcore and fiue leagues or miles in length. Another looketh towardes <hi>Spaine,</hi> and that longitude is an hundered and ſixty miles. The third, is oppoſed to the North,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12130:54"/>drawing moſt part towardes <hi>Germanie,</hi> and it is thought, that this way it containeth well tvvo hundred good miles. So that the whole Iſle may haue ſome fiue hundred miles in circuite.</p>
            <p>It hath a very ſerene and faire Hauen, and the habitation there is much more temperate then in <hi>France,</hi> and the colds are leſſe ſharp &amp; violent. <hi>Gallia trieme frigidior,</hi> by the iudgment of <hi>Petronius,</hi> and in mine vnderſtanding, ſo it is at this inſtant. In that Countrey are not to bee ſeene, the intollerable heats of Egypt, no more then the Ices of <hi>Sarmatia,</hi> all is temperate, all is cultiue, and all thinges are fruitfull there in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non illic Aries verno ferit aëra cornu</l>
               <l>nec Gemini praecedunt cornua Tauri</l>
               <l>Sicca Lycaonius reſupinant plauſtra Bootes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It hath a copious Sunne, Corne, Cloath, Wools, Waters, Beaſtes, Fiſh, Foule, and all kindes of wilde fleſh, in moſt great facility and felicity. Shee hath euen in her ſelfe, her <hi>India,</hi> and her <hi>Peru,</hi> not onely of Time, and of Iron, (as in the time of <hi>Caeſar</hi>) but likewiſe of Golde and Siluer: &amp; therefore ſhe vſeth not any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of Copper, Braſſe, or Annelets of Iron, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12130:55"/>to euen poize, but all fine Gold and Siluer. And ſuch is hir abounding in al kinds of riches, and in all thinges neceſſary for man: as (in due right) ſhe is confirmed by the Maiſter of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to be the firſt and principall of the fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Iſlands.</p>
            <p>She hath made plaine and ſmooth the backe of <hi>Thetis,</hi> by the number of her goodly &amp; great Shippes and Veſſelles: which doe ſerue her as bornes, as limits, as ramparts, and as wals.</p>
            <p>And ſhe is called <hi>Great,</hi> not for the extendure of her Landes, Countryes, and Prouinces; not ſo much for infinit multitude of people, for the great number of her Cities, Towns, Borroughs, and villages: as for the greatneſſe of courage in her Inhabitants, who neuer leaue winning, and neuer ſuffered themſelues to be foyled, or fully conquered.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Imperij fuerat Romani Scotia limes</l>
               <l>Romanae fuerit Scot-Anglus origo ruine.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But to conclude, the Kinges moſt glorious and pompous Title of Triumph, is to bee called <hi>DEFENDER OF THE FAITH,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is apparant, &amp; he ſhewes himſelfe more
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12130:55"/>affectionate, ardent, and zealous to preſerue, exalt, proclaime, and communicate it to them, which haue not as yet receiued it, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King on the earth. It is a Title, which giues him more glorye and ſplendour, then all his Scepters and Diadems. It honoureth him ſo much, as he ſhould not thinke himſelfe worthy to beare the name of King, if hee had not that withall of <hi>Defender of the Faith.</hi> It is a Tytle, which maketh him as much beloued of all, as that of King cauſeth him to bee feared. It is a Title, not as to day deſerued, and giuen to our Kings, but it is more then an hundered yeares, ſince it was giuen to his Maieſties great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth K. of <hi>Scots,</hi> as the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of M. <hi>Chambres</hi> do teſtifie. So that they deceiue themſelues, who thinke it is no longer, then ſince the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A glorious and Hereditary title, which you and we ought to eſteem, ſince it hath bin grauen in the fore-heads of the late Kings of either king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Yet a title not ſo much by ſucceſsion, as by merit &amp; acquiſition of a King, who fightes and beats down idolatry and Hereſy, more valiantly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12130:56"/>then all his Anceſtors. By a King, who ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the error, not onely of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> an Angle of the earth, but of the vvhole earth. For beholde, the dayes are comming, when God will punniſh the grauen Images of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that hee will make all her Countrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, and will cauſe al the wounds of death to fall in the midſt thereof. Theſe tidings ſhall come this year, and after this in the other, there ſhall be violence on the earth, and Ruler vpon Ruler.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Roma diu titubans varijs erroribus acta</l>
               <l>Coruet &amp; mundi deſinet eſſe caput.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wherfore, Go forth of her all people, to the end, that you be not partakers of hir ſins, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not hir plagus. Deliuer euery one his life, out of the heat of the wrath of the eternal. Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God, &amp; reſiſt no longer his reaſonable will, through a raſh kinde of zeale. There is no one of you ſo ignorant, but he knoweth moſt part of the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Romaine</hi> Church to be ſo euident, as the fautors and fauourers of them, can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger denie them. Seeke the truth, turn ouer the leaues of the Scriptures, which haue beene (for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12130:56"/>ſo long time) maliciouſly interdicted to you. None hath more or greater intreſt in your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, then your very ſelues.</p>
            <p>Yea, euen thou, who (with ſhame and falſe Enſignes) doeſt vſurp the Title of <hi>Holy Father, Lieutenant</hi> of God, <hi>Vicar</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Vice Deo, Vniuerſall</hi> Byſhop, Great <hi>Priest, Soueraign</hi> high Prieſt, <hi>Prince of Byshoppes, Heyre to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi> And you, who ſay of him, that for Primate he is <hi>Abell;</hi> For Gouernement, <hi>Noah;</hi> for his Patriarchate, <hi>Abraham;</hi> For Ordere, <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck;</hi> For Dignity, <hi>Aaron;</hi> For Authority, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> For Iudgement, <hi>Samuell;</hi> For Power, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and for <hi>Vnction,</hi> Chriſt. Thou that ſeateſt thy ſelfe in the Temple of God, aboue God, &amp; aboue all that is called God, to make thy ſelfe honoured as God. Thou that ſayeſt thou haſt power to bind Kings, to tie them in Chaines of Iron, to bereaue (&amp; at thy pleaſure) take away their Crownes, to breake their Scepters, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on their Crownes to giue their kingdomes as preyes, or otherwiſe to diſpoſe of them, to diſoblige their ſubiects from their oath of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and obedience: Repent thy ſelf of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, when both reaſon and Authoritie fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12130:57"/>Content thy ſelfe at leaſt, with the power limited by our learned <hi>Barcklay,</hi> cut off the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders which (like a crafty Serpent) haue crept into the Church, ſcratch and breake the head of thoſe Vipers of thy Paſtorall ſtaffe, caſt off alſo the ſin and corruption, ſo much as may be, not onely of thy Court, but of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet not of <hi>Rome</hi> alone, but of all thoſe places where thou art feared and reuerenced. Let the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her firſt ſplendour againe, that all abuſed may be beaten farre from her. Thou haſt a long time conuerted Lead into Gold, by meanes of thy Buls, which are but ſorry meat to ſatisfie fee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſpirits. Thy Pardons are too pardonous, and thy Indulgences haue too much indulgence; keepe them to thy ſourſe &amp; thy ſelfe. Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the power of them that haue giuen thee this power: <hi>Reddendo Caeſari quae ſunt Caeſaris, et quae ſunt Dei, Deo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you alſo, who will be Princes and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals altogether: You Prelates, Biſhops, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Prieſts, Prebends, &amp; all <hi>Romain</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of what order or name ſoeuer ye be, learn that it is now no longer time to reſiſt, you muſt bend or break vnder the yoake of the Sonne of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12130:57"/>God, and of his holy word.</p>
            <p>There hath bin ſleep enough, Luxury enough, Trafficke enough, &amp; enough of diſorderly wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the houſe of God, enough haue ye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your bellies and idleneſſe, enough haue ye pild &amp; pold the very fatteſt ſheepe in the flock, enough haue ye chopped, changed, bought, &amp; ſold in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the Lord. Awake now, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent iudgement, there is yet place for clemency and for mercy. The Synagogne of the Iewes, it is gone, the Law hath giuen place to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: by much more powerful reaſon then ſhold abuſe make way for purity; lying for truth; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions and Traditions of men, for the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, againſt which, let time bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo long, it preſcribeth nothing.</p>
            <q>Nec poterit ferrum, necedax abolere vetuſtas.</q>
            <p>I beſeech the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> to open the eyes and harts of Kings, of Magiſtrates, &amp; their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to the end, that in giuing place to his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly word, they may take knowledge of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt, and deteſting his yoake, they may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to that of Chriſt. To whom with the Father and the bleſſed Spirit, be Glory and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eternally, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
